<?xml version="1.0"?>
<conference>
  <title>Internet Librarian</title>
  <year>2008</year>
  <sessions>
    <session>
      <title>W1 &#x96; 130 Web Tips, Tricks, Tools, and Resources in 160 Minutes</title>
      <description>Get your coffee ready because you&#x2019;ll need to be wide awake for 3 hours of Steven Cohen&#x2019;s favorite online tips, tricks, tools, and&#xA0; esources. Cohen reveals which tools assist in making&#xA0; sers, colleagues, and family members happy. From Firefox plug-ins to Web 2.0 startups to mashups to RSS tricks, attendees of this workshop will leave with an arsenal of information and applications to bring back to their organizations. Knowledge is power, and this workshop assists librarians of all specialties in becoming current and up-to-date with the new and most exciting web tools available.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Cohen</last_name>
          <first_name>Steven M.</first_name>
          <job_title>Senior Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Law Library Management Inc.</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W2 &#x96; Screencasting 101: Creating Online Tutorials in Less Than 30 Minutes</title>
      <description>Online tutorials used to be extremely time intensive to create. With the increase in reference and instruction to distant users in all types of libraries and the need for just-in-time learning in many organizations, we need quicker ways to create tutorials to transfer information and demonstrate online library resources. New tools make it quick and easy to create online demonstrations and tutorials with a minimum of effort, to record screen actions, and to add a voice commentary. Explore using software such as Camtasia, Captivate, and Wink to quickly create online tutorials for your distance users.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Notess</last_name>
          <first_name>Greg</first_name>
          <job_title>Faculty &amp;amp; Graduate Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Montana State University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W3 &#x96; Not Just Facebook: Online Social Networks for Libraries</title>
      <description>While Bebo, Facebook, hi5, MySpace, and Orkut are among the better-known general online social networks, there is an ever-increasing number of online networks that have emerged for and within a wide variety of communities. Among many others, these include networks for academe and education (e.g., EduSpaces), ethnic groups (e.g., Black Planet), Boomers (e.g., Boomj), business (e.g., Linked-In), gay/lesbian/transgender groups (e.g., OUTeverywhere), religion (e.g., MyChurch), and researchers and scholars (e.g., Nature Network). This workshop provides an overview of the more significant niche online social networks, reviews their common and unique features and functionalities, and considers the potential opportunities for wider engaged library outreach to these communities. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;See blog entry/slides &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://nichesocialnetworksites.blogspot.com/2008/11/not-just-facebook-online-social.html" target="_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>McKiernan</last_name>
          <first_name>Gerry</first_name>
          <job_title>Science &amp;amp; Technology Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Iowa State University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W4 &#x96; Ajax for Libraries</title>
      <description>Learn all about the alternative approach to building web applications as seen in popular Web 2.0 sites such as Google Maps, Flickr, and Netvibes. Asynchronous JavaScript and XML (Ajax) is changing the way that users are able to interact with web applications and will change their expectations. This workshop introduces the concepts behind the Ajax method, provides examples of library applications of Ajax, and walks through the code that makes it all happen. It looks at the implications for next-generation library applications. Walk away with an understanding of Ajax, working examples of Ajax in action, and the confidence to start creating your own Ajax apps.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Clark</last_name>
          <first_name>Jason A.</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Initiatives Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Head of Digital Access and Web Services, Montana State University Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Coombs</last_name>
          <first_name>Karen A</first_name>
          <job_title>Senior Product Analyst for Web Services</job_title>
          <works_for>Developer Network, OCLC</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W5 &#x96; Integrating RSS Into Your Website</title>
      <description>RSS feeds are an excellent way to receive information from the internet. What many people don&#x2019;t know is that you can receive that information and easily repurpose and republish it on your website with little technical know-how. Imagine automatically posting up to date local or industry headlines on your library&#x2019;s homepage. This is what you can do in just a few simple steps. Our expert internet trainer shows you how. This workshop also covers additional RSS tools and services, including one that will create feeds from content without its own feed and another that will automatically turn your text-based content into a podcast.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Sauers</last_name>
          <first_name>Michael P</first_name>
          <job_title>Technology Innovation Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Technology &amp;amp; Access Services, Nebraska Library Commission</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W6 &#x96; Creative Training: Blending Technological Tools &amp;amp; Learning Styles</title>
      <description>This workshop examines how learning styles and learning theory can be applied to the latest technology tools. Instructional design,&#xA0; creation of learning outcomes, and assessment of technology effectiveness are explored. Get a better understanding of your target audiences and which tools will best suit their instructional goals. Perfect for any library staffers who want to learn how to create training modules using new technology tools, this workshop explores the different audience levels, evaluative measures that can be used in conjunction with cutting-edge technology tools and learning styles.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Norlin</last_name>
          <first_name>Elaina M</first_name>
          <job_title>Executive Director/Regional Library Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>African American Research Library and Cultural Grant, Broward County Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Travis</last_name>
          <first_name>Tiffini</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Instruction &amp;amp; Outreach, California State University - Long Beach</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W7 &#x96; Practical Project Management</title>
      <description>As we embrace new technologies and ways of working we often find ourselves in the new role of project manager, even though&#xA0; any of us have not been formally trained. In this train-the-trainer workshop, speakers will share a simple and practical approach that empowers staff and takes the fear and uncertainty out of project management. Based on a 3-hour workshop being delivered to library personnel at the UCSF Library, this session is full of practical ideas with step-by-step guidelines and two easy-to-use templates. Workshop leaders walk participants through the process, discuss the benefits of planning upfront, help eliminate the fear of setting deadlines, and talk about communication and participation issues. They demystify user roles, use case scenarios, and functional requirements.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Honey</last_name>
          <first_name>Sadie</first_name>
          <job_title>Internet Strategy and Project Management Consultant CivicActions</job_title>
          <works_for>UCSF Health Sciences Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Cameron</last_name>
          <first_name>Kathleen</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Content Development Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>UCSF Library &amp;amp; Center for KM</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Wolf</last_name>
          <first_name>Leslie</first_name>
          <job_title>Project Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>California Digital Library, University of California</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W8 &#x96; Working in Digital Branches</title>
      <description>So what&#x2019;s the difference between going to work in a building and seeing and talking with your colleagues and patrons &#x2026; and going to work digitally, connecting with your colleagues and patrons via web, voice, and webcam? And what&#x2019;s the difference in managing a team that works in the same building, and managing a team that has no building at all? Quite a bit, actually. Simply connecting people with technology doesn&#x2019;t mean things are going to go well. This workshop looks at what to consider when working digitally, &lt;br&gt;whether you are the manager or the team member: the roles, working approaches, and competencies that help make digital working environments work. Speakers share their years or experience and learnings, and, using the Topeka&amp;amp; Shawnee County Public Library&#x2019;s emerging digital branch as a case study and model, help you prepare to evolve your library to a digital branch model.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Jones</last_name>
          <first_name>Rebecca</first_name>
          <job_title>Partner</job_title>
          <works_for>Dysart &amp;amp; Jones Associates</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>King</last_name>
          <first_name>David Lee</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Services Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Topeka &amp;amp; Shawnee County Public Library and Publisher, davidleeking.com</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W9 &#x96; Searchers Academy: Searching 2.0</title>
      <description>Want to sharpen your skills? Find information in the real-time collaborative and social web? Learn from the experts? Join search veterans, speakers, authors, and columnists from &lt;i&gt;Searcher, ONLINE,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;EContent &lt;/i&gt;magazines and the Super Searcher series of books to learn the latest strategies and techniques for searching online. This fast-paced, newly designed, day-long event allows you to interact with the experts who share their searching secrets and expertise as they focus on the most-current practices in the field of web research. There&#x2019;s always something new to be learned from these leading-edge panelists. Participants should have basic experience with web searching, but even searchers with extensive internet background will find tips to polish and advance their skills and will certainlycome away with new resources and tools. Academy topics include:&lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Bates</last_name>
          <first_name>Mary Ellen</first_name>
          <job_title>Principal</job_title>
          <works_for>Bates Information Services, Inc.</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Phelps</last_name>
          <first_name>Marcy</first_name>
          <job_title>President</job_title>
          <works_for>Phelps Research Inc. Author, Research on Main Street: Using the Web to Find Local Business and Market Information</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Notess</last_name>
          <first_name>Greg</first_name>
          <job_title>Faculty &amp;amp; Graduate Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Montana State University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W10 &#x96; Web Managers Academy: Redesign 2.0</title>
      <description>Does your library website need to move to the next level? Does it need a visual makeover, social media tools, or new embedded services? Where do you start? One place to begin is by analyzing the strengths and weaknesses of your current site using analytic tools. Pick up new usability methods that can help you test proposed revisions early so that the new design doesn&#x2019;t just &#x201C;look&#x201D; better but also works better for the users. See how other libraries are using content management systems, user-generated content, database-driven content, federated search, and OpenURL resolvers to provide customized and personalized user content. Explore how social software applications including blogs, wikis, tagging, and RSS, fit in the mix. Pack your toolbox and take home tips, tools, checklists, and new design techniques that you can immediately put to use. Learn about common pitfalls and success factors for library redesigns. Topics and exercises include the redesign process; practical project management; web content management systems; usability and ethnographic methods: affinity mapping, photo reports, and map diaries.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Fichter</last_name>
          <first_name>Darlene</first_name>
          <job_title>GovInfo Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Saskatchewan Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Cervone</last_name>
          <first_name>Dr. Frank</first_name>
          <job_title>Managing Partner</job_title>
          <works_for>Cervone and Associates</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Wisniewski</last_name>
          <first_name>Jeff</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Pittsburgh</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Breeding</last_name>
          <first_name>Marshall</first_name>
          <job_title>Independent Consultant and Founder of Library Technology Guides</job_title>
          <works_for>Founder of Library Technology Guides</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W11 &#x96; Academic Libraries 2.0</title>
      <description>Libraries of all types have embraced Web 2.0 tools to provide innovative online services and reach out to their users. Academic libraries in particular have a unique opportunity to leverage the technologies and philosophy that drives Web 2.0 and Library 2.0 to meet the needs of their users. Join our panel of practitioners and experts as we explore some of the cutting-edge ways in which academic libraries are using Web 2.0 tools such as blogs, wikis, mashups, social bookmarking, and online social networks. This interactive session will also focus on some of the challenges around implementing these technologies such as getting buy-in from staff, administration, and patrons. A worthwhile workshopfor those interested in implementing changes to keep up with the 2.0 world.&lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Etches</last_name>
          <first_name>Amanda</first_name>
          <job_title>Head</job_title>
          <works_for>Discovery &amp;amp; Access, University of Guelph</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Griffey</last_name>
          <first_name>Jason</first_name>
          <job_title>Head of Library Information Technology</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Tennessee at Chattanooga Author, Speaker, Tech Geek</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Rogers</last_name>
          <first_name>Jenica P.</first_name>
          <job_title>Director of Libraries</job_title>
          <works_for>College Libraries, State University of New York at Potsdam</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Jastram</last_name>
          <first_name>Iris</first_name>
          <job_title>Reference &amp;amp; Instruction Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Carleton College</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Lawson</last_name>
          <first_name>Steve</first_name>
          <job_title>Humanities Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Colorado College</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W12 &#x96; Podcasting &amp;amp; Videocasting Boot Camp</title>
      <description>Podcasting is one of today&#x2019;s hottest social computing applications. But what can this emerging technology do for libraries? What is a videoblog and why use one on your library&#x2019;s website? This in-depth workshop, featuring two experts in the field of library podcasting and videocasting, answers these questions and more. Come explore and discuss how libraries are using podcasts and videocasts for outreach and learning through a variety of case studies, including tips on what types of content work best for different types of libraries. Detailed information on what to consider when planning for and implementing pod/videocasting at your library are provided along with an up-close and personal look at a variety of creation tools. Gain some hands-on experience in making podcasts and videocasts by producing content live during the session.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Free</last_name>
          <first_name>David W.</first_name>
          <job_title>Editor-in-Chief</job_title>
          <works_for>C&amp;amp;RL News, &amp;amp; Marketing &amp;amp; Communications Specialist, Association of College and Research Libraries (ACRL)</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>King</last_name>
          <first_name>David Lee</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Services Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Topeka &amp;amp; Shawnee County Public Library and Publisher, davidleeking.com</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W13 &#x96; Web Services for Libraries</title>
      <description>del.icio.us for subject guides, Flickr for library displays, YouTube for library orientation&#x2026;. Mashups and APIs (application programming interfaces) are becoming staples of modern web design. Libraries, as repositories of data, have a wealth of information that could be placed within the mashup context. With new tools and scripts available daily, it&#x2019;s becoming easier and easier to bring pieces of the web together and enable users to find and build new web services with library data. This workshop focuses on what an API is and what it can do, the standard components of web services, how to build a simple mashup with JavaScript, how to work with PHP to consume a web service and create a mashup, what web services and mashups mean for libraries, and how to start consuming and creating web services for your library with available tools and scripts. Come learn how open data standards and a little &#x201C;know-how&#x201D; can change your library services. Hear what others are doing and what you can do too. (Participants should be comfortable with HTML markup and have an interest in learning about web scripting and programming.)</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Clark</last_name>
          <first_name>Jason A.</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Initiatives Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Head of Digital Access and Web Services, Montana State University Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Coombs</last_name>
          <first_name>Karen A</first_name>
          <job_title>Senior Product Analyst for Web Services</job_title>
          <works_for>Developer Network, OCLC</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W14 &#x96; Project Management 101 for Libraries</title>
      <description>This half-day workshop explores the elements of successful project management and how projects might best be planned, implemented, and monitored. Aimed at anyone responsible for managing a project within their library or information organization, this interactive workshop encourages participants to share their own experiences and knowledge.&#xA0; It discusses key factors related to successful project management, methodologies and tools, proven techniques and tips for managing projects, and examples and case studies.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>O.B.E.</last_name>
          <first_name>Ms Mary Auckland</first_name>
          <job_title>Independent Consultant &amp;amp; Trainer</job_title>
          <works_for>I</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W15 &#x96; From Avatars to Advocacy: Innovation Through Un-Marketing</title>
      <description>There&#x2019;s no denying that the rise of social networking and Web 2.0 tools has created many new avenues for libraries to market themselves. But these marketing streams go much deeper than merely exploring new channels. They allow libraries to shift their focus and truly engage with their customers in remarkably effective online and in-person word of mouth marketing efforts. Come explore this shift in an innovative pre-conference lab that demonstrates and then walks participants through the creation of viral marketing ideas that enable customers to use the library brand to celebrate themselves. Participants are encouraged (but not required) to bring their own recording devices (digital video, still and audio, including upload cables) and laptops for creativity exercises.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Blowers</last_name>
          <first_name>Helene</first_name>
          <job_title>Community Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>OCLC</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Porter</last_name>
          <first_name>Michael</first_name>
          <job_title>President</job_title>
          <works_for>Library Renewal libraryman.com</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W16 &#x96; The Accidental Trainer</title>
      <description>If you are like most &#x201C;accidental&#x201D; library technology trainers, you are expected to take on computer training in your library, often with little or no previous experience or instruction. This workshop addresses the most common concerns of newly minted technology&lt;br&gt;trainers, recommends great tools and techniques, and shares helpful advice from many years of coordinating and providing training for libraries of all types around the country. If you are responsible for technology training &#x2014; whether in computer labs, classrooms,&lt;br&gt;or one-on-one with library users or staff &#x2014; join us for this workshop. You will learn why learning styles are important, how to create a learning community, strategies for communicating about technology, techniques for using activities, storytelling, and case studies to increase learning and retention.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Gerding</last_name>
          <first_name>Stephanie</first_name>
          <job_title>Independent Library Consultant</job_title>
          <works_for>Library Consultant &amp;amp; Author, The Accidental Technology Trainer: A Guide for Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Hough</last_name>
          <first_name>Brenda</first_name>
          <job_title>Continuing Education Consultant</job_title>
          <works_for>Northeast Kansas Library System</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W17 &#x96; Creative Digital Photography for Your Library</title>
      <description>Whether you have a standard website, a blog, or a wiki, text-only just won&#x2019;t cut it anymore. Come learn all you need to know to create, edit, and add images to your library website and how to take advantage of Creative Commons licensing to use others&#x2019; images on your site. This session covers not only licensing options but tips on choosing a digital camera, taking photos in your library, image editing, and managing your images.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Trainor</last_name>
          <first_name>Cindi</first_name>
          <job_title>Coordinator for Library Technology and Data Services</job_title>
          <works_for>Eastern Kentucky University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Sauers</last_name>
          <first_name>Michael P</first_name>
          <job_title>Technology Innovation Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Technology &amp;amp; Access Services, Nebraska Library Commission</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W18 &#x96; Beyond Podcasting: Making Stars</title>
      <description>You&#x2019;ve developed the ability to create a podcast but now what? This program shows you how to get the public (yes, even those who never visit your library) to listen and love your productions. Get past your fear of the mic and learn the professional tips that will give you a sound that your listeners will love. You&#x2019;ll get hints on how to take your production from facts to fantastic. And find out how to use social networks as the magnet to your podcasts. Come and experiment with your voice and interview skills and get lots of tips and tricks for engaging your customers.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Dowd</last_name>
          <first_name>Nancy</first_name>
          <job_title>Project Lead LibraryAware</job_title>
          <works_for>EBSCO Publishing Novelist</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W19 &#x96; Open Source CMS for Libraries</title>
      <description>In the last 5 years, library websites have grown in importance and size, creating a challenge for libraries in effectively and efficiently distributing the creation and maintenance of website content. At the same time, open source systems have gained popularity in libraries, and several open source content management systems have evolved that allow developers to easily extend existing functionality and add new Web 2.0 features. This intersection has presented libraries with the opportunity to implement open source content management systems to maintain their library websites. Learn about implementing an open source CMS for your library. This workshop will describe what a content management system is, provide an overview of the advantages to a library implementing a content management system, highlight several organizations using open source content management systems for their websites, discuss the process of selecting a CMS, and provide an overview of several content management systems. Explore WordPress, Joomla, and Drupal and see the basics of how to install and configure a basic website in each of these tools.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Coombs</last_name>
          <first_name>Karen A</first_name>
          <job_title>Senior Product Analyst for Web Services</job_title>
          <works_for>Developer Network, OCLC</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W20 &#x96; Project Management in Practice</title>
      <description>This workshop discusses different strategies and frameworks used by practitioners to manage projects in their libraries. These practitioners share their challenges, tips, tricks, and lessons learned in a variety of situations. Etches-Johnson focuses on project management in web redesign and discusses managing a project on a small scale, in fact where the project manager is also the project team! Blowers describes a systemwide approach to project management complete with sponsors, process owners, etc., at the Columbus Metropolitan Library (CML). She also talks about project management from the IT perspective, defining the role of process owners versus product owners as projects near completion and migration into maintenance and support roles. Hear from Phensuvabharp, CML lead project manager, who brings her firsthand knowledge to the conversation. Join this interactive session for practical approaches and techniques that you can use in any library or information environment.&lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>O.B.E.</last_name>
          <first_name>Ms Mary Auckland</first_name>
          <job_title>Independent Consultant &amp;amp; Trainer</job_title>
          <works_for>I</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Blowers</last_name>
          <first_name>Helene</first_name>
          <job_title>Community Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>OCLC</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Gilliam</last_name>
          <first_name>Macrina</first_name>
          <job_title>Applications Project Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Digital Services, Columbus Metropolitan Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Etches</last_name>
          <first_name>Amanda</first_name>
          <job_title>Head</job_title>
          <works_for>Discovery &amp;amp; Access, University of Guelph</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W21 &#x96; Games, Gaming, &amp;amp; Libraries</title>
      <description>If you don&#x2019;t know MMORPGs from DDR, this workshop is for you. It addresses two related aspects of gaming in libraries: hosting gaming events and gamings&#x2019; impact on learning. Learn how gaming can make your library more fun and how you can use gaming to participate in this developing form of literacy. Workshop attendees have the opportunity to play some games, increasing their understanding of gaming&#x2019;s appeal and possible applications in their environment.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Schmidt</last_name>
          <first_name>Aaron</first_name>
          <job_title>Principal</job_title>
          <works_for>Influx Library User Experience &amp;amp; Publisher, walkingpaper.org</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W22 &#x96; Dance, Dance, Library Evolution</title>
      <description>Today&#x2019;s librarian must be nimble and fast-moving.&#xA0;Librarians from different parts of the country and different areas of librarianship demonstrate what is emerging in their libraries and in their lives today: hot technologies, social networking, and services and tools for users. Enjoy this fast-paced, informative and interactive workshop from eight Twitter friends who are using these technologies to move themselves and their libraries beyond 2.0 and ahead of the curve.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Carscaddon</last_name>
          <first_name>Laura</first_name>
          <job_title>Instruction Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Undergraduate Services Team, The University of Arizona</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Harris</last_name>
          <first_name>Colleen S.</first_name>
          <job_title>Head of Access Services</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Tennessee &#x96; Chattanooga</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Neufeld</last_name>
          <first_name>Kenley</first_name>
          <job_title>Library Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Santa Barbara City College</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Stephens</last_name>
          <first_name>Courtney</first_name>
          <job_title>Electronic and Educational Resources Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Belmont University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Dene</last_name>
          <first_name>Jezmynne</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Portneuf District Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W23 &#x96; Advanced Screencasting: Tips &amp;amp; Tricks</title>
      <description>For those who would like to explore more advanced features of screencasting software, this in-depth workshop builds on Notess&#x2019; Saturday workshop and provides proven tips, techniques, and tricks to create compelling online tutorials. Using many examples, Notess explores using call outs, transitions, zooming, highlights, Flash quizzes, and many of the other advanced features of Camtasia Studio, Wink, Jing, and Captivate.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Notess</last_name>
          <first_name>Greg</first_name>
          <job_title>Faculty &amp;amp; Graduate Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Montana State University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W24 &#x96; Knowledge Structure, KM, &amp;amp; Traditional Library Skills</title>
      <description>This half-day workshop begins with a discussion of knowledge structures within organizations specifically how a library-KM (knowledge management) connection creates a framework that supports and takes advantage of a number of Web 2.0 social approaches combined with the use of natural category techniques. It then looks at KM and traditional library skills using a case study of collaboration between a KM consulting firm and two corporate librarians at a mid-sized company. The project was an early KM initiative that combined expertise location, taxonomy development, text analytics software, search, and ECM. It talks about what new skills the librarians needed to develop, how they learned from the KM team &#x2014; and how the KM team learned from them. It shares what worked smoothly and what needed some creative problem solving skills and provides tips on creating a learning experience for everyone, a flexible new approach that results in happy users.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Reamy</last_name>
          <first_name>Tom</first_name>
          <job_title>Chief Knowledge Architect</job_title>
          <works_for>KAPS Group</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Gaming &amp;amp; Gadgets Petting Zoo</title>
      <description>Join our gamers and gadget lovers for an evening of fun and playing. Bring your latest games and gadgets and try out each others&#x2019;. See if you are a guitar hero, winning Wii bowler/golfer, or rank as a dancing DDR expert. Led by gamer/gadget gurus Aaron Schmidt and Erik Boekesteijn, this evening is not only filled with fun, networking, and of course, learning and laughing but it introduces a new library game developed and designed by high school students in the Netherlands. See Dark Ink&#x2019;s world premiere! Refreshments included. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>OPENING KEYNOTE &#x97; Communities &amp;amp; Communication in a Social &amp;amp; Mobile World</title>
      <description>With all the social networking tools and wireless mobility available, there are more and more ways to reach our customers and communities. Our speaker, an early user of The WELL and student of virtual communities (in fact, many credit him with creating the term), an architect of HotWired and Electric Minds, and now an educator and consultant, talks about trends in the social and mobile world that information professionals need to understand and pay attention to both now and into the future. A colorful (as his painted shoes will attest) speaker, Rheingold is sure to delight, confound, and spark your ideas!</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Rheingold</last_name>
          <first_name>Howard</first_name>
          <job_title>Educator</job_title>
          <works_for>Consultant, &amp;amp; Author, Smart Mobs</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Coffee Break</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A101 &#x96; Super Searcher Shares: Search Tips Spectacular!</title>
      <description>One of IL&#x2019;s most popular sessions returns to turbo-charge your web research. Our confirmed super searcher and host of Searchers Academy provides an updated-to-the-minute and jam-packed-with-valuable-tips talk about searching the web more effectively. You don&#x2019;t need to be an expert to use these techniques, but even long-time researchers will learn from them.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Bates</last_name>
          <first_name>Mary Ellen</first_name>
          <job_title>Principal</job_title>
          <works_for>Bates Information Services, Inc.</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A102 &#x96; Searching Conversations: Twitter, Facebook, &amp;amp; the Social Web</title>
      <description>Many folks rely heavily on online social interconnections for fun, communication, and networking. Many of the social networks are partially or fully open to public view. See what information can be mined from the likes of Twitter, Facebook, Pandora, Amazon,&lt;br&gt;and any other new and popular individualized social services. Explore techniques for searching within and across these social tools, and learn what others may be able to find out about you.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Notess</last_name>
          <first_name>Greg</first_name>
          <job_title>Faculty &amp;amp; Graduate Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Montana State University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A103 &#x96; Search Widgets &amp;amp; Gadgets for Libraries</title>
      <description>As web content continues to grow and the signal-to-noise ratio increases, it has become important for libraries to find ways to get into users&#x2019; common web paths: the social networking sites such as Facebook, the web portals such as iGoogle, even learning management systems such as Blackboard. Clark looks at creating widgets or gadgets that allow users to have basic library search functions in these new user environments free from the catalog or library website. He shows live applications that provide different search functionality for library materials: a Google Gadget that allows gateway searching for library journals, books, and articles and a series of OpenSearch plug-ins that let patrons search library content from within the web browser. Donahue looks at creating user-activatedanimated research tools such as Flash-animated subject maps leading users directly to books. He also looks under the hood at the FLA files and design methodology and examines the underutilized applicability of Flash technology for library resources such as digital exhibits, online tutorials, and other types of library maps. Come learn about the simple tools and steps you can take in your library</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Clark</last_name>
          <first_name>Jason A.</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Initiatives Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Head of Digital Access and Web Services, Montana State University Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Donahue</last_name>
          <first_name>Tim</first_name>
          <job_title>Instruction Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Montana State University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A104 &#x96; Book Search &amp;amp; Catalog Search</title>
      <description>The first presentation focuses on search engines for e-books that can provide access to the text and metadata of ebooks on multiple sites. It discusses the process of developing and testing an ebook search engine, as well as the technical, bibliographic, and legal issues. It looks at the prospects for a low-cost search engine for law-related public domain ebooks and reports on the testing of various combinations of free crawlers, indexers, and search engines, as well as free or low-cost storage options. The second presentation illustrates one library&#x2019;s experience implementing the latest in catalog search technology, including visual search, relevancy ranking, spelling suggestions, RSS feeds, and enhanced content such as searchable chapter summaries. It discusses lessons learned, tips for getting buy-in from staff and customers, the next evolution of search, including creating a true&lt;br&gt;&#x201C;single search&#x201D; within your catalog that can pull all of your valuable content&#x2014;books, movies, databases, digital content, events&#x2014;into a single results list.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Frey</last_name>
          <first_name>Scott</first_name>
          <job_title>Reference Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Western State College of Law</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Armitage</last_name>
          <first_name>Maria</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Experience Analyst</job_title>
          <works_for>Digital Services, Columbus Metropolitan Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Barnes</last_name>
          <first_name>Amy</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Experience Analyst</job_title>
          <works_for>Digital Services Department, Columbus Metropolitan Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A105 &#x96; Search Tips &amp;amp; Keeping Current - What's Hot?</title>
      <description>Join our "keeping current" fanatic for his top tips on doing web &#xD;
research today and the hot new tools that he uses to keep his clients &#xD;
up to date with anything they need.&#xD;
</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Cohen</last_name>
          <first_name>Steven M.</first_name>
          <job_title>Senior Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Law Library Management Inc.</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A106 &#x96; Improving Navigation &amp;amp; Findability</title>
      <description>While semantic web ideas have been around for quite a while, the number of actual, practical applications has been low. However, by combining semantic web knowledge representations with faceted navigation techniques, media companies have been leading&lt;br&gt;the way to a first generation of applications. This session starts with a review and analysis of a large number of media internet sites and extracts some common themes and approaches, looks at what works well and what doesn&#x2019;t, and ends with a guide for developing the semantic web representations and facets and integrating them into a rich information display.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Reamy</last_name>
          <first_name>Tom</first_name>
          <job_title>Chief Knowledge Architect</job_title>
          <works_for>KAPS Group</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>EXHIBIT HALL GRAND OPENING RECEPTION</title>
      <description>Information Today, Inc. invites all conference registrants and exhibitors to a special Exhibit Hall opening reception on Monday,October 20. This is a great time to gather with fellow Internet Librarians and suppliers, renew acquaintances, meet new colleagues, sample tasty goodies, and check out the latest products and services in a relaxed atmosphere.</description>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Coffee Break</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B101 &#x96; Giving Your Marketing and Advocacy a Second Life</title>
      <description>You&#x2019;re using Flickr and blogs. You&#x2019;ve created social networks on MySpace and Facebook. You&#x2019;re IMing, texting, and twittering all day long. You&#x2019;ve even gained some notoriety on YouTube. Before your avatar drops from exhaustion, isn&#x2019;t it time you asked what all this 2.0 technology is really doing for your library? Learn the tricks to turn your mad Web 2.0 skills into effective marketing and advocacy results to increase exposure and support for your library. Dowd takes you to the next level by illustrating how to incorporate Web 2.0 technologies with traditional marketing and advocacy tools to produce effective results.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Dowd</last_name>
          <first_name>Nancy</first_name>
          <job_title>Project Lead LibraryAware</job_title>
          <works_for>EBSCO Publishing Novelist</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B102 &#x96; Digital Marketing: Successful Plans/Organizations</title>
      <description>A digital environment requires that library web managers think about outreach in a very different way. Our users may still frequent brick-and-mortar community establishments, but they spend more and more time online, in both solitary and social endeavors. How&lt;br&gt;do we, as their libraries, reach out to these users to help them find information? How do we reach them on their turf? Where is their turf? Learn about ways for all libraries to find potential users online. Where to spend your time to get the most bang for your buck and staff hours will be the focus, with tips for community websites, search engine placement, live assistance options, social networking sites, and much more. Take away a lengthy checklist of ideas to take back to your libraries to successfully create an ongoing online marketing plan.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Houghton</last_name>
          <first_name>Sarah</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>San Rafael Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Schmidt</last_name>
          <first_name>Aaron</first_name>
          <job_title>Principal</job_title>
          <works_for>Influx Library User Experience &amp;amp; Publisher, walkingpaper.org</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B103 &#x96; Making a Difference With Digital Media</title>
      <description>Every day, new opportunities arise for information professionals to establish their presence online. Done well, one&#x2019;s online identity can be a powerful tool for establishing professional credibility and marketing your skills to others. Schwartz highlights the various&lt;br&gt;tools for managing your online presence and provides tips and strategies for building a consistent, meaningful online identity. CML staff discuss their experiences integrating various Web 2.0 tools&#x2014;some difficult and some very simple&#x2014;into their websites. They talk about challenges and solutions and give lots of tips and tricks.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Schwartz</last_name>
          <first_name>Greg</first_name>
          <job_title>Library Systems Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Louisville Free Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Davis</last_name>
          <first_name>Samuel</first_name>
          <job_title>Application Solutions Architect</job_title>
          <works_for>Digital Services, Columbus Metropolitan Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Marlow</last_name>
          <first_name>Joy</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Experience Analyst</job_title>
          <works_for>Digital Services, Columbus Metropolitan Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B104 &#x96; Online Marketing &amp;amp; Promotion: Making It Fun &amp;amp; Economical</title>
      <description>More than just concrete buildings that loan books, libraries today are a collection of valuable resources: human, written, and electronic. Getting the word out to patrons about everything today&#x2019;s library has to offer can seem overwhelming. Claiborne focuses on ways to draw patrons into the library and get them involved and informed about programs, resources and opportunities. Stokes discusses reaching out to students, teaching them about the library&#x2019;s databases by using games, and to staff, keeping them informed about happenings in the virtual library. She talks about using blogs, vendor products, and open source products to create innovative ways to capture the attention of patrons, making it fun to use the online library.&lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Stokes</last_name>
          <first_name>Lauren P</first_name>
          <job_title>Virtual Library Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Las Vegas-Clark County Library District</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Boogaard</last_name>
          <first_name>Geert van den</first_name>
          <job_title>M.Sc.</job_title>
          <works_for>Innovation and funding, Delft Public Library (The Netherlands) BOOG Design and Advice</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B105 &#x96; Public Libraries &amp;amp; Web 2.0: Research Findings</title>
      <description>In the last few years, there has been much discussion and excitement over the implementation of Web 2.0 on public library websites as a means of reaching out to patrons. Many techniques have been shared, but this session focuses on the results of an bservational&lt;br&gt;study of public library websites in the U.S. searching for the presence of Web 2.0 technologies. It looks at how prevalent 2.0 technologies are and the characteristics of the libraries that are active in incorporating these technologies.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Lietzau</last_name>
          <first_name>Zeth</first_name>
          <job_title>Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Digital User Experience &amp;amp; Community Technology Center, Denver Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B106 &#x96; Public Library Issues &amp;amp; Reflections</title>
      <description>Join the day&#x2019;s speakers for an interactive, round-robin, expert response session with plenty of audience Q&amp;amp;A! Reflect on the day&#x2019;s insights and ideas and share your thoughts with colleagues.</description>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>EXHIBIT HALL GRAND OPENING RECEPTION</title>
      <description>Information Today, Inc. invites all conference registrants and exhibitors to a special Exhibit Hall opening reception on Monday,October 20. This is a great time to gather with fellow Internet Librarians and suppliers, renew acquaintances, meet new colleagues, sample tasty goodies, and check out the latest products and services in a relaxed atmosphere.</description>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Coffee Break</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C101 &#x96; Designing the Digital Experience Presentation</title>
      <description>New technology tools and techniques are changing the way users think about and interact with the websites they frequent. Businesses that recognize the radical shift in customer expectations know that usability isn&#x2019;t enough any more, and are increasingly obsessed with building websites and applications that deliver great user experiences. King explains the concepts behind designing experiences on the web, emphasizing current best practicesin three key areas: structure&#x2014;creating better experiences by improving a website&#x2019;sease-of-use; community&#x2014;memorable experiences and conversations created via online participation and community, the essence of Web 2.0; customers&#x2014;learn how to stage experiences online that are guaranteed to surprise and delight customers. Filled with practical tips on turning potentially negative experiences into memorable ones, this session provides lots of ideas to try on your website.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>King</last_name>
          <first_name>David Lee</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Services Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Topeka &amp;amp; Shawnee County Public Library and Publisher, davidleeking.com</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C102 &#x96; Fast &amp;amp; Easy Site Tune-Ups</title>
      <description>Looking for ways to speed up, clean up, and optimize your site with minimal effort? These 35 1-minute upgrades show you how to fine-tune your site&#x2019;s code, design, and structure to make your site faster, more flexible, and more standards-compliant. Do one, do 10, or do them all to maximize your site&#x2019;s performance in minimal time.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Wisniewski</last_name>
          <first_name>Jeff</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Pittsburgh</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C103 &#x96; Web Site Assessment With Google Analytics</title>
      <description>With the investments that libraries make in developing websites, it is critical to constantly measure use levels, discern patterns and trends, and spot hotspots and areas of strengths, as well as areas that aren&#x2019;t working like you anticipated. Google Analytics, a free service offering a very sophisticated approach to website analytics, enables libraries to use methodologies well tuned in the ecommerce arena such as action-oriented web development and search engine optimization. Breeding demonstrates how he uses Google Analytics to assist in the management of sites such as Library Technology Guides, the Vanderbilt Television News Archive, and components of the Vanderbilt University Library&#x2019;s web presence.&lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Breeding</last_name>
          <first_name>Marshall</first_name>
          <job_title>Independent Consultant and Founder of Library Technology Guides</job_title>
          <works_for>Founder of Library Technology Guides</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C104 &#x96; Cool Tools for Library Webmasters</title>
      <description>Hop on board and look at some great tools that can help make your life easier and delight or even wow your visitors. Our experts and popular speakers are back with a whole new roster of free or inexpensive tools covering the gamut of Web 2.0 gadgets and widgets, hosted applications, server side scripts, and desktop tools. They highlight tools for people who are just starting out as well as some advanced applications for webmasters who like to dig their teeth into a bit of code. Pick up some new tool ideas that can take your site to the next level.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Cervone</last_name>
          <first_name>Dr. Frank</first_name>
          <job_title>Managing Partner</job_title>
          <works_for>Cervone and Associates</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Fichter</last_name>
          <first_name>Darlene</first_name>
          <job_title>GovInfo Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Saskatchewan Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C105 &#x96; Mashing Up and Remixing the Library Website</title>
      <description>Libraries today are presented with the challenge creating a unified &#xD;
user experience out of systems which are traditionally highly &#xD;
separate silos. Often this is done by literally copying and &#xD;
inserting data and information from one system to another. In the &#xD;
case of the library website data is often copied from the library &#xD;
catalog, article databases or other sources. However, this method &#xD;
is neither efficient nor sustainable. As a result, the University &#xD;
of Houston Libraries has developed a home grown content management &#xD;
system based on the following principles of Web 2.0: Radical &#xD;
decentralization, Small pieces loosely joined, and Remixable &#xD;
content. This tool allows librarians to create web pages that are a &#xD;
mix of types content from various systems including events, finding &#xD;
aids, blogs, library catalog, and federated search. By using this &#xD;
tool, subject librarians can create highly specialized "virtual &#xD;
libraries" for their users in a particular subject area. &#xD;
Additionally, content from the library website and other systems &#xD;
can now be incorporated into external websites such as those for &#xD;
colleges and departments. This innovation has allow the library to &#xD;
better serve its users by presenting them accurate, up to date, and &#xD;
relevant information.&#xD;
</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Coombs</last_name>
          <first_name>Karen A</first_name>
          <job_title>Senior Product Analyst for Web Services</job_title>
          <works_for>Developer Network, OCLC</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Vacek</last_name>
          <first_name>Rachel</first_name>
          <job_title>Head of Web Services</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Houston</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C106 &#x96; Facebook &amp;amp; Libraries: Ethnographic Evaluation</title>
      <description>Social networking sites such as Facebook present libraries with unique opportunities for reaching students. Many users, however, perceive Facebook as primarily &#x201C;social&#x201D; space, and the presence of professors, librarians, or parents can be intrusive, unwelcome, or just plain &#x201C;weird&#x201D; to the very students being targeted. Find out how George Washington University&#x2019;s Gelman Library worked with an anthropologist to carry out a mixed methods study to identify unspoken rules and patterns of behavior to guide libraries&#x2019; Facebook efforts and discover what our users want. Learn how Gelman implemented and refined their Facebook campaign based on the study results. Explore the merits of anthropological research in evaluating these new, social technologies.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Bietila</last_name>
          <first_name>David</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Services/Reference Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>George Washington University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Edwards</last_name>
          <first_name>Elizabeth M</first_name>
          <job_title>Reference/Technology Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Gelman Library, George Washington University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Bloechl</last_name>
          <first_name>Christopher</first_name>
          <job_title>Ethnographic Consultant</job_title>
          <works_for>George Washington University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>EXHIBIT HALL GRAND OPENING RECEPTION</title>
      <description>Information Today, Inc. invites all conference registrants and exhibitors to a special Exhibit Hall opening reception on Monday,October 20. This is a great time to gather with fellow Internet Librarians and suppliers, renew acquaintances, meet new colleagues, sample tasty goodies, and check out the latest products and services in a relaxed atmosphere.</description>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Coffee Break</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D101 &#x96; ITIL &amp;amp; Digital Libraries</title>
      <description>It seems that no matter who you talk to, everyone claims to use best practices. While most people would consider this a good thing, the problem with best practices is that discovering and implementing them are not always an obvious or easy task. A relatively little&lt;br&gt;known but extremely influential set of best practices in information technology is the ITIL (Information Technology Infrastructure Library). With the recent release of version 3 of the ITIL, this framework has taken the information technology world by storm in both thecommercial and nonprofit worlds. Our IT expert talks about what the ITIL is, where it fits into the digital library development landscape, and how you can start using it to improve the outcomes of your digital library projects.&lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Cervone</last_name>
          <first_name>Dr. Frank</first_name>
          <job_title>Managing Partner</job_title>
          <works_for>Cervone and Associates</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D102 &#x96; Digital Preservation Solutions</title>
      <description>LOCKSS (Lots of Copies Keep Stuff Safe) is an international nonprofit community initiative that provides tools and support so libraries can easily and cost-effectively preserve today&#x2019;s web-published materials for tomorrow&#x2019;s readers. Hear more about this approach to digital preservation strategies for libraries, and how it is being implemented today. Then learn about another approach relating to digital preservation of electronic journals. Both speakers discuss the challenge of protecting materials and provide examples of their solutions.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Newell</last_name>
          <first_name>Patrick</first_name>
          <job_title>Electronic Resources Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>LOCKSS Program, California State University, Fresno</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>DiFiore</last_name>
          <first_name>Ken</first_name>
          <job_title>Associate Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Library Relations, Portico</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D103 &#x96; Passion, Participation, &amp;amp; Digital Projects</title>
      <description>This session focuses on the new learnings and new ways of working based on the experience of an aboriginal digital project. It includes discussions of Lucene/Solr faceted browse implementation, seven institutional partner collections, aboriginal community advisors/consultations, grad students who wrote interpretive essays/exhibits, 3D video of artifacts, digital rescue of museum vintage AV recordings, and more.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Fichter</last_name>
          <first_name>Darlene</first_name>
          <job_title>GovInfo Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Saskatchewan Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D104 &#x96; Practical Guide to a User-Focused Digital Library</title>
      <description>This session elaborates on the various aspects of building, managing, and promoting a digital library including tools to build and evaluate a digital library, digital content licensing, and tips on how to promote the use of this content. So if you&#x2019;re looking to come away with a better understanding of the essential practices, tools, and tips that are important in user-focused digital libraries, this is a session you must attend.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Guevara</last_name>
          <first_name>Sophia</first_name>
          <job_title>Research Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>R</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Zhu</last_name>
          <first_name>Qin</first_name>
          <job_title>Information Developer</job_title>
          <works_for>HP Labs</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D105 &#x96; E-Copyright: Online Tools</title>
      <description>As librarians, understanding our (and our institutions&#x2019;) rights and responsibilities under copyright law is perhaps even more important in the digital age. Although it can be confusing and kind of scary, it won&#x2019;t just go away. Unfortunately, misinformation abounds. From expanded services from the Copyright Clearance Center to ALA&#x2019;s Copyright Advisory Network and more, there are plenty of online resources to help you understand and manage this increasingly vital and complex concern. Learn about what&#x2019;s available and how to use it.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Anderson</last_name>
          <first_name>Freya</first_name>
          <job_title>Head</job_title>
          <works_for>Public Services, Alaska State Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Sauers</last_name>
          <first_name>Michael P</first_name>
          <job_title>Technology Innovation Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Technology &amp;amp; Access Services, Nebraska Library Commission</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D106 &#x96; Instant Audio &amp;amp; Video: Tools Igniting the Digital World</title>
      <description>No time to learn how to podcast or make videos? Seesmic, Utterz, ooVoo, BlogTV, Qik, and Talkshoe are just a few of the new audio and video tools letting people create their own instant web content with a small learning curve. Some are meant for short, quick thoughts by individuals on the go, others for longer conversations among a group connected to the web. Compare these exciting new tools and discuss their roles in community building and collaboration.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Crosby</last_name>
          <first_name>Connie</first_name>
          <job_title>Principal</job_title>
          <works_for>Crosby Group Consulting</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>EXHIBIT HALL GRAND OPENING RECEPTION</title>
      <description>Information Today, Inc. invites all conference registrants and exhibitors to a special Exhibit Hall opening reception on Monday,October 20. This is a great time to gather with fellow Internet Librarians and suppliers, renew acquaintances, meet new colleagues, sample tasty goodies, and check out the latest products and services in a relaxed atmosphere.</description>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>OPENING KEYNOTE &#x97; Search Engine Land: What's Happening Out There?</title>
      <description>Our keynote speaker, one of the world&#x2019;s leading search engine gurus and internet pioneers as well as a popular IL speaker, examines how things have changed in the search space, and makes his predictions of what we should be looking at in the coming year. He discusses the implications of the evolving changes for internet librarians and gives us some insight as to what to expect in 2009. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Sullivan</last_name>
          <first_name>Danny</first_name>
          <job_title>Editor In Chief</job_title>
          <works_for>Search Engine Land</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A201 &#x96; Enterprise Trends: Beyond the Simple Intranet</title>
      <description>So you&#x2019;ve got an intranet. It&#x2019;s OK but it&#x2019;s not shaking the organization&#x2019;s foundations. What next? You&#x2019;ve got a platform now that links everyone in the organization to you and your content vault. You&#x2019;re licensing external content, and you&#x2019;re building links to internal content and resources. What are the trends to build on this foundation? This session discusses the big trends in the enterprise space&#x2014;mobile, white label social networks, visual search, faceted search, software as a service, OpenURL, federated search, and more. Join one of IL&#x2019;s most admired speakers who has tracked trends in the library, technology and information space for more than a decade and blogs these trends at the popular Stephen&#x2019;s Lighthouse blog. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Abram</last_name>
          <first_name>Stephen</first_name>
          <job_title>Principal</job_title>
          <works_for>Lighthouse Consulting Inc.</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A202 &#x96; Finding Corporate Knowledge</title>
      <description>Organizations large and small recognize that intellectual capital goes largely unused because it is not findable. Staff reinvent the wheel every time a new project or proposal is undertaken when they could repurpose already existing in-house resources and information, if only they could find it. Instead of using their time to create new information, they are spinning their wheels recreating content. Using two case studies from the nonprofit and corporate worlds, this session discusses finding and sharing information using enterprise-wide search software, Web 2.0 tools, better organization, and staff training. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Hunt</last_name>
          <first_name>Deb</first_name>
          <job_title>Library Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Mechanics' Institute &amp;amp; Principal, Information Edge</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A203 &#x96; Revitalizing Content in the Enterprise</title>
      <description>Dissatisfied with out-of-the-box OPAC interfaces, some libraries have recently introduced third-party search technology to resuscitate their catalogs. In 2007, the IDA Library took this approach and partnered with an enterprise search and clustering technology company to provide not only a face-lift to its catalog but to create a single, enterprise-level information discovery tool. The first presentation explores how librarians can transplant and revitalize catalog metadata in a new host recipient of enterprise search. The second case study focuses on communicating content to clients and how one team promotes research and library resources to audiences around the company through as many channels as they can, including blogs, wikis, mailing lists, RSS, surveys, social bookmarking, old-fashioned tabling, and other methods. The third talk discusses the use of alerting services, including the different types of topics and ways in which information can be searched and retrieved as well as the many delivery mechanisms available.&lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Connell</last_name>
          <first_name>Christopher J.</first_name>
          <job_title>Information Integration Analyst</job_title>
          <works_for>Library, Institute for Defense Analyses</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Draper</last_name>
          <first_name>Karen</first_name>
          <job_title>Senior Information Specialist</job_title>
          <works_for>Adobe Systems</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Shem-Tov</last_name>
          <first_name>Emily R</first_name>
          <job_title>Research Portal Program Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Global Market Research &amp;amp; Planning, Adobe Systems</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Affelt</last_name>
          <first_name>Amy</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Database Research, Compass Lexecon</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Networking Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A204 &#x96; Law Library 2.0</title>
      <description>How do you introduce 2.0 technologies into the law firm library? Law firms are notoriously slow in adopting new technologies and are often steeped in the traditional. In the first presentation, learn how creative law librarians spearheaded a project to create a firm intranet in a culture that doesn&#x2019;t embrace technology or sharing easily. Working with several other departments the speakers bridged the gap between many different user groups with competing ideas and helped lead the change through collaboration as they introduced the law firm to new technologies. They share how they used focus groups, marketing, and involved key users to &#x201C;sell&#x201D; the intranet, first to management, then to staff; what tools were used to create buy-in; and the strategies that were involved, as well as experiences with an internal wiki as a project management tool for the intranet and a way to introduce library staff to 2.0 technologies in a user-friendly format that spawned other uses, including collaboration, policy development, resource sharing, training, and more. Drawing from her experience as a law firm library director, Crosby provides additional examples and describes where law libraries are headed next. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>MLS</last_name>
          <first_name>Camille Reynolds</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Knowledge Management, Nossaman LLP</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Juliano</last_name>
          <first_name>Liana</first_name>
          <job_title>Technical &amp;amp; Electronic Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Nossaman LLP Vice President/President Elect American Indian Library Association</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Crosby</last_name>
          <first_name>Connie</first_name>
          <job_title>Principal</job_title>
          <works_for>Crosby Group Consulting</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Lapachet</last_name>
          <first_name>Ms. Jaye A. H.</first_name>
          <job_title>Manager of Library Services</job_title>
          <works_for>Coblentz, Patch, Duffy &amp;amp; Bass LLP</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A205 &#x96; SharePoint for Libraries: Streamlining Your Intranet Management</title>
      <description>Combining WYSIWYG web editing with blogs, calendars, discussion boards, RSS, and other Web 2.0 innovations, Microsoft SharePoint has been adopted by many institutions as an easy way to create a self-propagating intranet. With staff able to edit pages, upload documents, and have discussions, SharePoint can seem to be a panacea. Two expert library web managers who have been through pilots, implementations, and staff rollouts share their experiences and give you the best advice they have on rolling out similar projects in your own library. Take away tips, tricks, and hacks to make your own library&#x2019;s Share-Point rollout that much easier. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Houghton</last_name>
          <first_name>Sarah</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>San Rafael Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Staley</last_name>
          <first_name>Shannon M.</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Technology &amp;amp; Social Sciences Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>San Jose State University Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B201 &#x96; Innovation</title>
      <description>Moving from &#x201C;best practice&#x201D; to &#x201C;fresh practice&#x201D; means more then just tuning up a successful idea. To truly create &#x201C;fresh practice,&#x201D; you must reexamine, revisit, and readjust to new trends and changing community indicators to avoid merely redoing yesterday&#x2019;s leftover ideas. This session explores current cultural indicators affecting digital services in libraries and suggests a framework for developing strategies in fresh practices. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Blowers</last_name>
          <first_name>Helene</first_name>
          <job_title>Community Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>OCLC</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B202 &#x96; Fostering Creativity &amp;amp; Innovation in Your Staff</title>
      <description>When trying to foster new learning and innovative services in libraries we often hear from staff that there&#x2019;s not enough time set aside to do that kind of work. What if staff could have a good chunk of time to work on a self-directed project that had essential and strategic benefit to the library? It would be like having your own Fulbright Scholar&#x2019;s program. PLCMC started a new program that offered any staff member who proposed a viable project, a 6-month sabbatical from their regularly assigned duties to learn, develop, and design a new program or service. This session showcases two of the four projects that have been completed, discusses staffing implications, offers a viewpoint from other library departments affected by these new projects and workloads, and shows how this program has seeded new ideas and innovations. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Gullett</last_name>
          <first_name>Matt</first_name>
          <job_title>Emerging Technology Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Public Library of Charlotte &amp;amp; Mecklenburg County (PLCMC)</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Kozak</last_name>
          <first_name>Tom</first_name>
          <job_title>Library Assistant</job_title>
          <works_for>Public Library of Charlotte &amp;amp; Mecklenburg County (PLCMC)</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Cole</last_name>
          <first_name>Tom</first_name>
          <job_title>Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Public Library of Charlotte &amp;amp; Mecklenburg County (PLCMC)</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Villo</last_name>
          <first_name>Paul De</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Services Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Charlotte Mecklenburg Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B203 &#x96; Embedding Libraries/Librarians in Learning</title>
      <description>The change imperative facing libraries challenges us to become proactive partners in the academic learning environment, collaborating with faculty and instructional technologists as courses are developed to integrate resources and learning objects, support the implementation of information-rich and research-based learning activities, and participate in the learning assessment and course evaluation. To develop this level of collaboration, librarians need new frameworks, new tools, and new capabilities to engage in these dynamic partnerships. Hear how one library, an early adopter, has embedded expertise and services in the learning process as a strategic imperative. Learn about the strategies, frameworks, and capabilities being used to leverage today&#x2019;s technology. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Wallace</last_name>
          <first_name>Dr. Deb</first_name>
          <job_title>Managing Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Baker Library Services, Knowledge &amp;amp; Library services, Harvard Business School</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Networking Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B204 &#x96; Who Moved My Ultrafiche &amp;amp; 8-Tracks? Insights for the Future</title>
      <description>After 50 years observing, using, and developing library technology, Dan Lester has learned things that will help libraries to do better with further developments of services to clients. Librarians who succeed do so because they&#x2019;ve been willing to experiment and to fail; they&#x2019;ve tried technologies that died and some that never really lived, as well as those that have evolved. So few are willing to discuss their &#x201C;failures&#x201D; that it is often difficult for others to learn from them. As with all electronic technologies, those used by libraries have gotten smaller, faster, and more interconnected, thus improving the services libraries can provide and giving them the opportunity to develop ones unimagined a decade or two ago. Few libraries can deal with all of them at once, but trying many and developing a selected few will lead to greater successes for the library and for the clients. Which ones should you try? How can you improve your chances of success? How do you convince your managers to let you try new things? Our experienced IL veteran discusses these and shares his learnings.&lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Lester</last_name>
          <first_name>Dan</first_name>
          <job_title>Head</job_title>
          <works_for>Network Services, University Libraries, Boise State University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B205 &#x96; Ubiquitous Computing &amp;amp; Libraries</title>
      <description>Ubiquitous computing (ubicomp) is defined as &#x201C;a model of human-computer interaction in which information processing has been thoroughly integrated into everyday objects and activities.&#x201D; As opposed to the desktop paradigm, in which a single user consciously engages a single device for a specialized purpose, someone &#x201C;using&#x201D; ubiquitous computing engages many computational devices and systems simultaneously, in the course of ordinary activities, and may not necessarily be aware of it. Ubicomp will soon be a lynchpin for libraries attempting to be more meaningfully integrated into patrons&#x2019; everyday lives, both online and offline. This session provides a glimpse of the future and discusses how the latest ubicomp tools relate to the mission of libraries, research, forecasts, and evolving implications. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Porter</last_name>
          <first_name>Michael</first_name>
          <job_title>President</job_title>
          <works_for>Library Renewal libraryman.com</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Peters</last_name>
          <first_name>Chris</first_name>
          <job_title>Technical Writer and Technology Analyst</job_title>
          <works_for>MaintainIT Project TechSoup</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C201 &#x96; LOL @ Your Library: Live Online Learning</title>
      <description>Live Online Learning brings your library&#x2019;s programs to remote staff and patrons. Eliminate travel, save money and time using synchronous web conferencing tools and virtual environments. This session covers key considerations in live online learning, from selecting synchronous learning platforms (conferencing/virtual environments) to developing a staff training plan, creating and facilitating online events, and finally, web development and IT considerations, including archiving online programs for 24/7 access.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Villo</last_name>
          <first_name>Paul De</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Services Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Charlotte Mecklenburg Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Cole</last_name>
          <first_name>Tom</first_name>
          <job_title>Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Public Library of Charlotte &amp;amp; Mecklenburg County (PLCMC)</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Musselman</last_name>
          <first_name>Dale</first_name>
          <job_title>OCLC Online Computer Library Center</job_title>
          <works_for>Inc.</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C202 &#x96; 2.0 Learning &amp;amp; 1.8 Users: Bridging the Gap</title>
      <description>For many instruction librarians, the challenge of Library 2.0 isn&#x2019;t the technology, it&#x2019;s the users. Despite the extreme 2.0 savvy attributed to the Millennials in the buzz that dominated early 2.0 reports, the media is finally catching up to what many instruction librarians have known all along: The Google Generation may need some help moving from passive consumer to active participant in the read/write web. Join two academic library instruction librarians for a discussion of challenges in and suggestions for bringing students, professors, librarians, and IT staff onto page 2.0 and why doing so is an important first step in bringing about Library 2.0 services and technologies our communities can embrace. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Leon</last_name>
          <first_name>Rudy</first_name>
          <job_title>Outreach &amp;amp; Instruction Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Nevada, Reno</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Harris</last_name>
          <first_name>Colleen S.</first_name>
          <job_title>Head of Access Services</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Tennessee &#x96; Chattanooga</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C203 &#x96; Podcasting &amp;amp; Video Tutorials: Designing, Creating, &amp;amp; Making Them Work</title>
      <description>The first presentation offers an analysis of available free and fee &#xD;
screen capture software, as well as strategies, techniques, and tips for &#xD;
creating videos that will get the point across and engage users to create &#xD;
effective learning tools. It covers what software may be right for you, how to &#xD;
create a video with Camtasia, guidelines to follow when scripting and capturing &#xD;
your video, and where to market your videos so they are as accessible as &#xD;
possible. The second presentation looks at a variety of creation tools and &#xD;
outlines "must do's" for planning, creating and using podcasting and video &#xD;
training tools in the public library setting.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Alford</last_name>
          <first_name>Emily</first_name>
          <job_title>Reference and Technology Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Michigan State University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Schroeder</last_name>
          <first_name>Heidi M</first_name>
          <job_title>Health Sciences Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Michigan State University Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>King</last_name>
          <first_name>David Lee</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Services Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Topeka &amp;amp; Shawnee County Public Library and Publisher, davidleeking.com</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Networking Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C204 &#x96; Streaming Media &amp;amp; Re-Tooling Library Services for Online Learners</title>
      <description>As enrollment in online and distance courses grows, academic libraries can&#x2019;t afford for out-of-sight students to be out of mind. This session offers ideas, tips and tricks for retooling library services to address the needs of online students via voice and video over the internet and web-based interactive tutorials. SJSU SLIS, the number one elearning library science program in the world, offers students, faculty, alumni, and the broader library community a large body of content through its website using the SLIS Media Player. Speakers explore the tools and technologies utilized to deliver streaming content, as well as the production process of organizing speakers and collaborating with professionals in the field to create compelling web content. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>David</last_name>
          <first_name>Dale</first_name>
          <job_title>Instructional Media Developer</job_title>
          <works_for>San Jose State University School of Library Information Science (SJSU SLIS)</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Bernier</last_name>
          <first_name>Anthony</first_name>
          <job_title>Assistant Professor</job_title>
          <works_for>San Jose State University School of Library Information Science (SJSU SLIS)</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Stillwell</last_name>
          <first_name>Barbara</first_name>
          <job_title>Multimedia QA Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Public Services, National University Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Lockerby</last_name>
          <first_name>Robin</first_name>
          <job_title>Assistant Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Public Services, National University Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C205 &#x96; Blending Technologies for Library Promotion &amp;amp; Instruction</title>
      <description>Do you have an online tutorial or instruction session that needs a little 2.0 face-lift? Hear first how a group of librarians and students at UMBC Library used a mix of basic video production and screen recording and capture technologies to create a video clip for library promotion and instruction. The blending of technologies, digital storytelling, and embedded learning objects has led to greater interest in its potential. Then see how the Learning Information Literacy Online (LILO) tutorial at the University of Hawaii uses interactivity and 2.0 tools to teach fundamental information literacy concepts as it reinforces the skills students need to produce college-level research papers and presentations. It also looks at how information literacy can be integrated into assignments, courses, and academic programs, enabling users to create personalized research journals and more.&lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Chang</last_name>
          <first_name>May</first_name>
          <job_title>Assistant Director</job_title>
          <works_for>LibraryTechnology, East Carolina University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Hanson</last_name>
          <first_name>Margot</first_name>
          <job_title>Instruction &amp;amp; Outreach Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>California Maritime Academy</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Roddy</last_name>
          <first_name>Kevin M.</first_name>
          <job_title>Associate Professor</job_title>
          <works_for>Information Literacy Librarian, University of Hawaii, Kapiolani Community College</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D201 &#x96; Solving the Reference Desk Problem</title>
      <description>The Darien Library&#x2019;s new building will have a virtual reference department, roving librarians with hand-held internet tablets, and no reference desk. Sheehan shows how the library is moving reference beyond the desk, beyond the technological trappings of Library 2.0, and revolutionizing public services. Murphy and Peterson detail the results of their reference via SMS programs. Suggested best practices and guidelines for iPhone applications and mobile reference services are shared. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Sheehan</last_name>
          <first_name>Kate</first_name>
          <job_title>Open Source Implementation Coordinator</job_title>
          <works_for>Bibliomation ALA TechSource Blogger</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Murphy</last_name>
          <first_name>Joe</first_name>
          <job_title>Library Directions &amp;amp; Tech Trends Analyst. Director Library Futures.</job_title>
          <works_for>Library Future Innovative Interfaces, Yale Uni</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Peterson</last_name>
          <first_name>Ellen</first_name>
          <job_title>Public Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Maui Community College</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D202 &#x96; Solving the Money Problem</title>
      <description>Once upon a time in a small town in the West, a girl looked at her library&#x2019;s 1990s-style FrontPage website and thought, &#x201C;I could do better.&#x201D; Or more precisely, she thought, &#x201C;Hey, anything Aaron Schmidt and Jessamyn West can do well, I can do poorly.&#x201D; One Word-Press download, a few Google accounts, some shoestring usability testing and she was on her way. Crossett shows how you too can use open source software, free web tools, social networking, and sheer dumb persistence to create a website for your library. Articles and blog posts about Web 2.0 and Library 2.0 can sometimes seem impossible to implement in smaller, poorer, and/or under-technology-staffed libraries. This doesn&#x2019;t mean that these librarians can&#x2019;t offer excellent online services to their users! Houghton-Jan covers 20 easy steps that libraries can take to improve websites with ease. If your library hasn&#x2019;t yet implemented the newest and greatest technologies on its website but wants to, this is the session for you. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Crossett</last_name>
          <first_name>Laura</first_name>
          <job_title>Branch Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Park County Library System</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Houghton</last_name>
          <first_name>Sarah</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>San Rafael Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D203 &#x96; Solving the OPAC Problem</title>
      <description>SOPAC (Social OPAC) has come a long way since first released in January 2007. Blyberg highlights some of the features behind version 2.0 and explains the three-tiered architecture&#x2014;the ILS-independent abstraction layer, the Drupal module, the open social repository&#x2014;and demonstrates how easy it is to install and deploy SOPAC 2.0. Barr focuses on strategies for building a well-integrated website, and uses as a case study the launch of Villanova University&#x2019;s library site. He demonstrates how making intelligent design decisions and implementing the open source OPAC overlay VuFind enables his website to enhance library brand recognition.&lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Blyberg</last_name>
          <first_name>John</first_name>
          <job_title>Assistant Director for Innovation and User Experience</job_title>
          <works_for>Darien Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Barr</last_name>
          <first_name>Christopher</first_name>
          <job_title>Design &amp;amp; Interface Specialist</job_title>
          <works_for>Villanova University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Networking Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D204 &#x96; Solving the Interest Problem</title>
      <description>In Charlotte, North Carolina, the behavior of youthful offenders who have been exposed to video games, the internet, Web 2.0 tools, and even Teen Second Life has significantly improved. Czarnecki gives details about the program and illustrates how it can be useful for your library. Macias and the librarians at Portland Community College worked hard to interact with their students through MySpace. He&#x2019;ll tell how they moved beyond having a stagnant presence on the site and used it to develop real connections and generate interest in the library. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Czarnecki</last_name>
          <first_name>Kelly</first_name>
          <job_title>Technology Education Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>ImaginOn, Public Library of Charlotte &amp;amp; Mecklenburg County (PLCMC)</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Landis</last_name>
          <first_name>Cliff</first_name>
          <job_title>Technology Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Valdosta State University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D205 &#x96; Solving the Buy-In Problem Interactive Discussion, Speakers From the Day, &amp;amp; Audience</title>
      <description>One of the central issues in implementing new technology in the library, even if it does a good job solving problems, is staff and management buy-in. We&#x2019;ll learn from the successes of the day&#x2019;s speakers and find out how they dealt with resistance and communication issues. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>CT-T1 &#x96; Business Info Online: Super Searcher Strategies</title>
      <description>Author of six online research books, Bates provides tips for conducting business research online and staying current on new business and finance information.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Bates</last_name>
          <first_name>Mary Ellen</first_name>
          <job_title>Principal</job_title>
          <works_for>Bates Information Services, Inc.</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>CT-T2 &#x96; Chrome 101: Google's New Browser</title>
      <description>Come and hear the highlights of Google&#x2019;s new browser, Chrome, and why you may or may not want to use it. Join this up-to-the-minute briefing which is filled with insights and tips.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Breeding</last_name>
          <first_name>Marshall</first_name>
          <job_title>Independent Consultant and Founder of Library Technology Guides</job_title>
          <works_for>Founder of Library Technology Guides</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>CT-T3 &#x96; Drupal 101</title>
      <description>Drupal is a free, open source web content management system that has been gaining interest in the library world. Drupal offers a flexible&#xA0; modular configuration that allows website creators to incorporate functionality such as content description, blogs, forums, tagging, groups, and more! This intro gives you the basics on drupal and demos some drupal-based library websites.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Etches</last_name>
          <first_name>Amanda</first_name>
          <job_title>Head</job_title>
          <works_for>Discovery &amp;amp; Access, University of Guelph</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>CT-T4 &#x96; Connecting With the Millennium Generation</title>
      <description>How do you relate with the Millennium Generation who constantly interact, form networks, gather information and assess reliability of information, particularly through the use of social network sites such as Facebook and MySpace. Come explore ideas on what types of information services will be relevant to the new generation of workers and how info pros can build a presence in the social network sites that the Millennium Generation use in order to effect relevant outreach to this group.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Bates</last_name>
          <first_name>Mary Ellen</first_name>
          <job_title>Principal</job_title>
          <works_for>Bates Information Services, Inc.</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>CT-T5 &#x96; Microformats: Big Ideas in Small Packages</title>
      <description>Microformats are a set of simple open data formats used to describe people, events, and things that humans can read and from which computers can also read and extract information. Learn what microformats are all about, see how to create information in microformat format using easy online tools, and learn about the benefits of making microformats part of your website today!</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Wisniewski</last_name>
          <first_name>Jeff</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Pittsburgh</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>CT-T6 &#x96; Web 2.0 for Faster Government Information</title>
      <description>&#xD;
This cybertour looks at the cool Web 2.0 tools and government information resources that can help you to keep up with the huge amounts of government information available today.&#xD;
</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Scheeder</last_name>
          <first_name>Donna</first_name>
          <job_title>Deputy Chief Information Officer</job_title>
          <works_for>Congressional Research Service, Library Of Congress</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>CT-T7 &#x96; Libraries of the Future</title>
      <description>This cybertour discusses an initiative launched by the U.K.&#x2019;s Joint Information Systems Committee (JISC) as part of its mission to provide world-class leadership in the innovative use of ICT (information, communications and technology) to support education and research.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>O.B.E.</last_name>
          <first_name>Ms Mary Auckland</first_name>
          <job_title>Independent Consultant &amp;amp; Trainer</job_title>
          <works_for>I</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>CT-T8 &#x96; Using RSS, Podcasts, &amp;amp; XML to Deliver Rich-Media Content</title>
      <description>Traditional methods of distributing library content are failing to keep up with the quickness and accessibility of online distribution models. Google, iTunes, Netflix, and Amazon are working to move data to users faster than libraries can. This cybertour takes a look at the new&#xA0; options libraries have for pushing full-text content and other media to where our users are.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Clark</last_name>
          <first_name>Jason A.</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Initiatives Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Head of Digital Access and Web Services, Montana State University Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>CT-T9 &#x96; A Quick Tour of Info Island</title>
      <description>This cybertour provides a quick tour of the resources and facilities available on Info Island in Second Life. Seeing is understanding, and this tour allows you to see Second Life &#x2013; and Info Island &#x2013; for yourself. Info Island was the first land mass purchased for libraries, librarians and library patrons. Since its founding, a growing number of allied islands have joined what is now called the Info Island Archipelago.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Trueman</last_name>
          <first_name>Rhonda</first_name>
          <job_title>Access Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Learning Resources Center, Northwest Florida State College</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>CT-T10 &#x96; Twitter Tips &amp;amp; Tricks</title>
      <description>So you know how to use the basics of Twitter, but are you getting the most out of microblogging posts by others? Learn how you can use Twitter feeds from conferences, and more.&lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Sauers</last_name>
          <first_name>Michael P</first_name>
          <job_title>Technology Innovation Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Technology &amp;amp; Access Services, Nebraska Library Commission</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Burns</last_name>
          <first_name>Christa</first_name>
          <job_title>Special Projects Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Nebraska Library Commission</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Good Internet Librarian Practices Worldwide</title>
      <description>Join the Shanachie Tour and hear about the latest excursions and findings from libraries around the world - Jamaica, the Netherlands, North America, and more! Over coffee and cookies, be inspired by the Shanachie group&#xED;s enthusiasm and video skills and learn about some exciting practices around the world. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Boekesteijn</last_name>
          <first_name>Erik</first_name>
          <job_title>founder and director Doklab</job_title>
          <works_for>Doklab ShanachieTour</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Geer</last_name>
          <first_name>Jaap Van de</first_name>
          <job_title>Delft Public Library</job_title>
          <works_for>D</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>OPENING KEYNOTE &#x97; Social Media &amp;amp; Networked Technologies: Research &amp;amp; Insights</title>
      <description>Join our exciting expert &#x2014; an academic, researcher and blogger &#x2014; as she shares research and insights around social network sites like Friendster, MySpace, and Facebook; youth culture; how observing and blogging can create a career; online culture; trends that Internet Librarians should be watching in the future, and more. You won't want to miss this stimulating event. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>boyd</last_name>
          <first_name>danah</first_name>
          <job_title>Ph.D. student</job_title>
          <works_for>School of Information at Berkeley, School of Information at Berkeley &amp;amp; Fellow, Harvard Berkman Center for Internet &amp;amp; Society</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A301 &#x96; Strategic Framework for Library Automation</title>
      <description>Blogs, wikis, social tagging, and other Web 2.0-inspired constructs, now commonplace, have become their own silos within the libraries&#x2019; overall web presence. It&#x2019;s time for Web 2.0 to grow up and move into the strategic infrastructure that supports the library mission. No longer should blogs and wikis exist as stand-alone tangents and social computing be an afterthought to the overall computing environment. Breeding proposes a transformation of the way libraries approach their web presence that systematically blends Web 2.0 concepts into the fabric of its supporting technologies. Hear his tips for building on what we&#x2019;ve learned from Web 2.0 to create an enterprise environment that more effectively supports the strategic mission of libraries. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Breeding</last_name>
          <first_name>Marshall</first_name>
          <job_title>Independent Consultant and Founder of Library Technology Guides</job_title>
          <works_for>Founder of Library Technology Guides</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A302 &#x96; Implementing the Next-Gen OPAC</title>
      <description>From selection to implementation to federated search integration to evaluation, learn from one library&#x2019;s experience navigating the &#x201C;next-gen&#x201D; waters. Find out what we knew, what we learned, what we wished we had known, and get insights into all that is Next Gen OPAC. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Wisniewski</last_name>
          <first_name>Jeff</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Pittsburgh</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Reception - In the Exhibit Hall</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A303 &#x96; Web 2.0 Tools for Online CM Workflow &amp;amp; Intranets</title>
      <description>This session shares secrets for enhancing online user experience via a dynamic environment for collaboration, sharing, interaction, and accessing content and services. Chase discusses how to engage library staff and users in blogs, wikis, podcasts, and other social software to build online communities and platforms for interacting with online users. Chang discusses best practices for managing internal information and documents by using a wiki to build an intranet and deal with the library&#x2019;s internal documents. The last presentation provides another case study of using a wiki to build a library staff intranet with multiple editors and the necessary training for intranet content providers. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Chase</last_name>
          <first_name>Darren</first_name>
          <job_title>Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Southampton, Stony Brook University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Balsamo</last_name>
          <first_name>Joseph</first_name>
          <job_title>Assistant Director of Library Information Systems</job_title>
          <works_for>Health Sciences Library, Stony Brook University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Chang</last_name>
          <first_name>May</first_name>
          <job_title>Assistant Director</job_title>
          <works_for>LibraryTechnology, East Carolina University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Moss</last_name>
          <first_name>Heather</first_name>
          <job_title>Bibliographic Coordinator</job_title>
          <works_for>Bibliographic &amp;amp; Medadata Services, UMBC Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Griffis</last_name>
          <first_name>Patrick</first_name>
          <job_title>Business Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University Libraries, University of Nevada, Las Vegas</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Yunkin</last_name>
          <first_name>Michael</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Content Manager &amp;amp; Usability Specialist</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Nevada</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A304 &#x96; Information Visualization Tools</title>
      <description>From library catalogs to mind maps to visual search engines join us as we tour some of the best, most interesting, most useful, or just plain coolest&#xA0; visualization tools out there.&#xA0; One of the most important trends to emerge from the Web 2.0 phenomenon is the advent of&#xA0; visualization tools that can illuminate, reveal, and shine a bright light on otherwise complex, dense, or dare we say boring data and text. Explore how these tools offer unique ways to visualize information patterns, facilitate information discovery and navigation, and reveal hidden concepts. Find the sweet spots for these new visualization tools for libraries, including how library users responded when the library&lt;br&gt;catalog went "visual" with AquaBrowser.&lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Fichter</last_name>
          <first_name>Darlene</first_name>
          <job_title>GovInfo Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Saskatchewan Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Wisniewski</last_name>
          <first_name>Jeff</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Pittsburgh</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B301 &#x96; Defining &amp;amp; Measuring Social Media Success</title>
      <description>Libraries are becoming increasingly present in the social media sphere on sites such as Facebook, Flickr, and YouTube, to mention a few. Once you&#x2019;re there, however, how do you know if you&#x2019;re having an impact? How do you measure success? This session takes a look at developing a social media plan, defining relevant goals and objectives, and looks at a number of useful free online tools to help track and measure your social media efforts. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Wisniewski</last_name>
          <first_name>Jeff</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Pittsburgh</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B302 &#x96; Twitter &amp;amp; How the "Twittest" Use It for Keeping Up</title>
      <description>The session focuses on the latest in micro-blogging: Twitter. The point of Twitter is to answer the question &#x201C;What are you doing now?&#x201D; in 140 characters or less via the web, client software, IM, or SMS. The first presentation shares the ups and downs of Twitter along with reporting on the results of several librarian- and library-based Twitter experiments. The second presentation by Next Gen librarians reviews the use of social networking tools to stay on top of hot technologies and new developments including how to weave Twitter streams, RSS feeds, online bookmarks, and information shared over social networking sites such as Facebook and LinkedIn into a professional development tool that will help you keep up with ease. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Sauers</last_name>
          <first_name>Michael P</first_name>
          <job_title>Technology Innovation Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Technology &amp;amp; Access Services, Nebraska Library Commission</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Burns</last_name>
          <first_name>Christa</first_name>
          <job_title>Special Projects Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Nebraska Library Commission</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Trainor</last_name>
          <first_name>Cindi</first_name>
          <job_title>Coordinator for Library Technology and Data Services</job_title>
          <works_for>Eastern Kentucky University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Dene</last_name>
          <first_name>Jezmynne</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Portneuf District Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Reception - In the Exhibit Hall</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B303 &#x96; Making Movies: Cameras, Lights, Action</title>
      <description>Hear from an InfoTubey (a YouTube library marketing award) winner how to make a movie. Robinson covers everything from coming up with the original idea, scripting, storyboarding, casting, finding locations that work, lighting and editing. The focus is on how to make movies on a budget and demystify the entire process so that you feel you can make movies too. In fact, participate as our speaker and the audience make a 60-second movie in the session and see how easy it really is. NOTE: The presenters request that attendees&#xA0;of this session bring 13 business cards and their cell phones!&lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Robinson</last_name>
          <first_name>Sean</first_name>
          <job_title>IT Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Allen County Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Gregg</last_name>
          <first_name>Kaye</first_name>
          <job_title>Video Production</job_title>
          <works_for>Allen County Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B304 &#x96; What's Hot in RSS &amp;amp; Social Software</title>
      <description>Social software is rapidly changing the way we provide information to our consumers, work together in an organizational structure, and communicate. Going beyond SEs, this session highlights cutting-edge tools and techniques for libraries, hot new trends, resources, and advice. Jam-packed with Cohen&#x2019;s A&#x2013;Z listing of the hot social software and RSS tools on the market today, there will also be time for the audience to highlight favorite social software tools. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Cohen</last_name>
          <first_name>Steven M.</first_name>
          <job_title>Senior Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Law Library Management Inc.</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C301 &#x96; Virtual Worlds, Real Libraries</title>
      <description>The Gartner Research Group predicts that by 2011, 80% of internet users will participate in a virtual world. Should libraries be pioneering these virtual worlds&#x2014;and just what is the role of libraries in virtual worlds? This overview of virtual worlds and what libraries are doing in them comes from serious practitioners who highlight librarians and projects featured in their book and share many tips and insights. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Trueman</last_name>
          <first_name>Rhonda</first_name>
          <job_title>Access Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Learning Resources Center, Northwest Florida State College</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C302 &#x96; Digital Games in European Libraries</title>
      <description>Despite steady integration into a common European Union, each European nation retains certain individual elements of infrastructure. Libraries, for example, tend to follow different policies and systems in different countries. This talk examines one aspect of library activity across Europe: the implementation and use of digital games. By studying some rich and varied examples of game use, several important questions are addressed: Why do some library digital games services flourish in some European countries but not in others? Is access to games affected by library funding, technological progress, legal restrictions, or national attitudes toward digital games? Are there models of game use in European libraries that could be replicated in American libraries? Discussion of these issues highlights both the barriers and opportunities for the technology and suggests ways for implementing digital games in libraries in the future. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Kirriemuir</last_name>
          <first_name>Mr John</first_name>
          <job_title>Consultant &amp;amp; Researcher</job_title>
          <works_for>Silversprite</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Reception - In the Exhibit Hall</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C303 &#x96; Creating Games &amp;amp; Services With Digital Natives</title>
      <description>In the first presentation, hear from experienced team leaders about the challenges and excitement working with adolescents in the creation of a &#x201C;library&#x201D; game. Learn the strategies and implementation plans for creating the &#x201C;Dark Ink&#x201D; game with students from the Netherlands, and gain insights about how to do something creative like this in your environment. Buckland, a recent grad, and Godfrey discuss the challenges of chat with avatars and reference services in virtual worlds such as Second Life. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Boekesteijn</last_name>
          <first_name>Erik</first_name>
          <job_title>founder and director Doklab</job_title>
          <works_for>Doklab ShanachieTour</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Geer</last_name>
          <first_name>Jaap Van de</first_name>
          <job_title>Delft Public Library</job_title>
          <works_for>D</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Buckland</last_name>
          <first_name>Amy</first_name>
          <job_title>eScholarship</job_title>
          <works_for>ePublishing &amp;amp; Digitization Coordinator, McGill University Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Godfrey</last_name>
          <first_name>Krista</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Memorial University of Newfoundland</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C304 &#x96; Second Life Library Profiles</title>
      <description>In the virtual world Second Life, libraries have become integral parts of many online communities yet still have a number of unique challenges. Some arise from the nature of the virtual environment, others from the fact that all our patrons are highly sophisticated computer users. This session describes the role of libraries in the Second Life, focusing on the Alexandrian Free Library System which is a consortium of community-based libraries operating in Second Life, including the communities of Caledon and Steelhead. Caledon is a large community where the library system resembles a real-life public library system with several neighborhood branches. Steelhead is a small town that recently decided to open its own public library. Using "images from the field" to show the libraries' presence, our speakers look at how the libraries were created; how their online collections are selected and organized; and how their reference service, online exhibits, book groups, poetry readings, storytelling, and other activities have become an integral part of these online social networking communities. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Hewlett</last_name>
          <first_name>Jean</first_name>
          <job_title>Regional Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of San Francisco</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Jacobson</last_name>
          <first_name>J.J.</first_name>
          <job_title>Associate Curator for American Culinary History</job_title>
          <works_for>William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan Graduate School of Library and Information Science, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D301 &#x96; Crafting the User-Centered Library</title>
      <description>This session presents practical methods for gathering data from users in a variety of ways for user-centric design, including techniques for implementing what your users need and want, and how to overcome the obstacles that may pop up. Learn how to make your library evolve, bit by bit, into the library your users have always dreamed of! Full of insights, concrete examples, and tips to use in your library. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Landis</last_name>
          <first_name>Cliff</first_name>
          <job_title>Technology Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Valdosta State University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D302 &#x96; Strategic Planning 2.0</title>
      <description>This session looks at the learnings from one university while engaging all staff in creating an updated 5-year strategic plan that recognized that improved uses of technology were key elements in developing both better user-centric services and staff computing skills. By using Web 2.0 applications such as wikis and blogs, the staff was introduced to the power and ease of social networking tools, incorporated new technologies into staff workflows, and allowed everyone to participate in the strategic planning process. Once exposed to collaborative networking technologies, staff further adopted these tools for improved documentation of numerous changing operations, procedures, and policies. Gain tips and ideas from their experience. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>White</last_name>
          <first_name>Dr Andrew</first_name>
          <job_title>Director Health Sciences Library</job_title>
          <works_for>Stony Brook University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Reception - In the Exhibit Hall</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D303 &#x96; Pecha Kucha - Conversation Face-Off!</title>
      <description>Pecha Kucha is Japanese for the sound of conversation and represents a fast-paced series of presentations. Each of our panelists has 6 minutes and 40 seconds along with 20 images to express their opinion about planning and management strategies and techniques in libraries. Each takes a view&#x2014;planning frameworks, project management, marketing, customer relations, and more. See if they can do it and then join in the conversation about 2.0 technology tools and tricks. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Schwartz</last_name>
          <first_name>Greg</first_name>
          <job_title>Library Systems Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Louisville Free Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Jones</last_name>
          <first_name>Rebecca</first_name>
          <job_title>Partner</job_title>
          <works_for>Dysart &amp;amp; Jones Associates</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Abram</last_name>
          <first_name>Stephen</first_name>
          <job_title>Principal</job_title>
          <works_for>Lighthouse Consulting Inc.</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Dowd</last_name>
          <first_name>Nancy</first_name>
          <job_title>Project Lead LibraryAware</job_title>
          <works_for>EBSCO Publishing Novelist</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Norlin</last_name>
          <first_name>Elaina M</first_name>
          <job_title>Executive Director/Regional Library Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>African American Research Library and Cultural Grant, Broward County Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D304 &#x96; Library Floor Plans 2.0</title>
      <description>Space, and the management of it, is a challenge that besets every library; however, the more you know about what you have, the better you can manage it. A geographic information system (GIS) is a configuration of computer hardware, software, and personnel specifically designed for the acquisition, maintenance, and use of geographically referenced data. This session gives an overview of GIS and discusses its relevance to libraries. It looks at how one library partnered with its technology department to create a GISbased spatial information manager for the library to serve a wide range of applications including facilitating the analysis and optimization of existing space within the library, serving as a real-time high-quality map generator, providing access to the square footage of any room in the library, assisting reference librarians in their efforts to direct students to resources in the library, facilitating disaster planning, and more. Cox shows actual highquality maps generated by the system and discusses its integration with Google Earth. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Cox</last_name>
          <first_name>Thom</first_name>
          <job_title>Technical Project Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Tisch Library, Tufts University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>CT-W1 &#x96; Social Networks for Business/Professional Use</title>
      <description>Hear how social network tools such as Facebook, LinkedIn, Xing, Plaxo, and Naymz are being used for business/professional use, while others like MySpace are NOT useful in this context. Looks at unique characteristics and provides tips for getting the most out of these tools.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Hulser</last_name>
          <first_name>Richard P.</first_name>
          <job_title>Chief Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Natural History Museum of Los Angeles County</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>CT-W2 &#x96; Organization 2.0</title>
      <description>This talk looks at the characteristics of the &#x201C;organization 2.0&#x201D; and how libraries are recreating their structures and processes to thrive in a new environment. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Jones</last_name>
          <first_name>Rebecca</first_name>
          <job_title>Partner</job_title>
          <works_for>Dysart &amp;amp; Jones Associates</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>CT-W3 &#x96; New Roles for Info Pros</title>
      <description>This cybertour looks at some of the interesting roles and jobs that information professionals have these days. Join us and be inspired!&lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Kneale</last_name>
          <first_name>Ruth A</first_name>
          <job_title>Systems Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>ATST, National Solar Observatory</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>CLOSING KEYNOTE &#x97; Learning &amp;amp; Play in a Social &amp;amp; Mobile World</title>
      <description>User-focused tools help information professionals to connect and integrate our activities and resources into our clients&#x2019; and communities&#x2019; workflows and lives. Those that are fun and easy really grab those customers and communities! Lawley looks at new opportunities and challenges resulting from social and mobile technologies and practices, discusses recent research and trends, and provides thought-provoking insights for us as we plan for the future. &lt;br&gt;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Lawley</last_name>
          <first_name>Elizabeth Lane</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>RIT Lab for Social Computing, Rochester Institute of Technology</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
  </sessions>
</conference>
