<?xml version="1.0"?>
<conference>
  <title>Internet Librarian</title>
  <year>2011</year>
  <sessions>
    <session>
      <title>Library Camp Monterey@Monterey Public Library</title>
      <description>Join us at the Monterey Public Library for an interactive discussion about Revolutionizing the Net With Content, Connections, &amp;amp; Conversations in our communities. We&#x2019;ll talk about people, technology, and libraries, so bring your war stories and your questions and be prepared to share &#x2014; this is definitely not a &#x201C;sage on the stage&#x201D; event. (PowerPoints are forbidden!) This unstructured conversation may range from web presence to user experience to info commons to everything in between that affects all types of libraries.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Buckland</last_name>
          <first_name>Amy</first_name>
          <job_title>eScholarship</job_title>
          <works_for>ePublishing &amp;amp; Digitization Coordinator, McGill University Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Data Curation: Understanding &amp;amp; Dealing With Research Data</title>
      <description>In the past few years, &#x201C;data deluge&#x201D; has become a topic of concern for federal agencies, grant funders, scholars, and librarians. What is going to happen to all the data that is being generated by researchers? And what should&#xA0;be the role of librarians in this evolving area of scholarly communication? &#xA0;One approach to address these issues led to the development of the Data&#xA0;Curation Profile, a tool for information professionals to gather information&#xA0;about a specific set of research data that may be published, shared, or&#xA0;archived for reuse and dissemination. Researchers at Purdue University&#xA0;Libraries and the Graduate School of Library and Information Science at University of Illinois, with support from the Institute of Museum and Library Services, developed this tool as a means of investigating, uncovering, and capturing the data needs of researchers. Through hands-on activities, this&#xA0;full-day workshop covers how the Data Curation Profile was designed, provides a template and approaches for using it to interact with researchers,&#xA0;and illustrates the types of information it gathers and the various scenarios&#xA0;for which the profiles can be useful. Registration is free for attendees registered for Internet Librarian 2011. Register early for this free workshop as&#xA0;attendance is limited to 40. Lunch is not included.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Brandt</last_name>
          <first_name>Scott</first_name>
          <job_title>Associate Dean for Research</job_title>
          <works_for>Purdue University Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Carlson</last_name>
          <first_name>Jake</first_name>
          <job_title>Data Services Specialist</job_title>
          <works_for>Libraries, Purdue University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W1 &#x96; Measures That Perform</title>
      <description>What&#x2019;s a meaningful measure, a measure that really &#x201C;performs&#x201D;? It&#x2019;s a measure that matters to your decision makers and demonstrates that your services are making a meaningful difference to the library&#x2019;s community, campus, or organization. While Jones has yet to find that &#x201C;one&#x201D; magic performance measure during 30 years of working in this sector, she has found, through work with government, academic, public and corporate libraries, an approach and framework to successfully identify, manage and communicate measures meaningful to decision makers. Workshop leaders discuss today&#x2019;s useful measures for communicating value and for operational and management purposes. They work with attendees to apply the framework and examples to their situations.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Jones</last_name>
          <first_name>Rebecca</first_name>
          <job_title>Partner</job_title>
          <works_for>Dysart &amp;amp; Jones Associates</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Hosseini-Ara</last_name>
          <first_name>Moe</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Culture, City of Markham Markham Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Silk</last_name>
          <first_name>Kimberly</first_name>
          <job_title>Data Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Martin Prosperity Institute, University of Toronto</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W2 &#x96; Analyzing Website Usage With Google Analytics</title>
      <description>This interactive workshop introduces Google Analytics, a powerful, easy-to-use, and free website usage measurement tool. Participants learn how to set up, collect, monitor, and intelligently analyze their website usage data to better understand their users and their sites. Users will leave the session ready to implement Google Analytics on their library sites and make use of its powerful visualizations to make informed decisions about site structure and content.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Wisniewski</last_name>
          <first_name>Jeff</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Pittsburgh</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Fichter</last_name>
          <first_name>Darlene</first_name>
          <job_title>GovInfo Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Saskatchewan Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W3 &#x96; Managing Projects &amp;amp; Communication</title>
      <description>This informative and interactive workshop is for those looking for a better way to organize and standardize their development process, keeping track of project details while improving transparency within departments and the library. It shows how to gain control in managing your projects and improving communication about your projects. Scrum, an agile development methodology, is often used to manage software development, but it can be expanded to other project management tactics. Learn about the benefits of Scrum, the terminology, the processes, and the roles. Additionally, hear about the successes and challenges of the implementation of Scrum at the University of Houston Libraries, and take home the Scrum process to get started in your institution.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Vacek</last_name>
          <first_name>Rachel</first_name>
          <job_title>Head of Web Services</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Houston</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Watkins</last_name>
          <first_name>Sean</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Developer</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Houston</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W4 &#x96; Best Practices for Mobile Reference Services</title>
      <description>Today, it is crucial that libraries offer services on mobile platforms. More people are texting than talking and accessing the internet from their cell phones. The My Info Quest (MIQ) collaborative text message reference project, now 2 years old, includes libraries from all over the U.S. MIQ was the first collaborative text message reference service. Librarians involved in the project share tips for best practice, success for other libraries that want to start a service, and results of evaluation activities to date.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Bell</last_name>
          <first_name>Lori</first_name>
          <job_title>School of Library and Information Science</job_title>
          <works_for>San Jose State University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Peters</last_name>
          <first_name>Tom</first_name>
          <job_title>CEO</job_title>
          <works_for>TAP Information Services OPAL, Trendy Topics, Unabridged, My Info Quest</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Galik</last_name>
          <first_name>Barbara</first_name>
          <job_title>Executive Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Cullom-Davis Library, Bradley University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W5 &#x96; Redesign for UX: Website Usability</title>
      <description>Website design is about more than choosing pretty colors. This interactive workshop takes you through the steps of a website redesign process, including the very important step of usability testing. Usability testing ensures your users&#x2019; experience (UX) is positive and successful. After this workshop, participants will be able to identify the aspects of their websites that are worth saving, the parts that need to change, and how to make it happen. The focus is on the desired end results and user needs, not coding!</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Etches</last_name>
          <first_name>Amanda</first_name>
          <job_title>Head</job_title>
          <works_for>Discovery &amp;amp; Access, University of Guelph</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W6 &#x96; Building a Community-Led Service Philosophy Framework at Your Library</title>
      <description>Based on the thriving community-led service framework developed by Edmonton Public Library, this workshop discusses how EPL implemented their approach through staff involvement and feedback and how EPL developed a community-led toolkit to guide staff in connecting with communities and better understanding community needs.&#xA0; This session discusses EPL's community profiles, ways EPL is using technology outside the library walls and conclude with best practices and successes to help you develop your library's community-led service framework. There will be time for interaction and sharing.</description>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W7 &#x96; Engaging Your Community With QR Codes</title>
      <description>QR codes are emerging as a mobile technology to bridge the digital and physical worlds. This workshop covers the basics of QR codes&#x2014;what they are, how to make them, how to use them, what resources are necessary, etc. It then moves onto creative ways communities are using them to engage their audience within and beyond libraries&#x2014;scavenger hunts through town, learning to use the academic library, marketing, and information delivery. It covers the new opportunities for libraries that QR codes represent: expanding concepts of resource discovery, facilitating patron use of mobile devices to connect with the library and its resources, and renewing/re-imagining uses of library space. Join our active QR gurus and learn everything you need to know about QR codes and libraries: their applications, the practical steps and concerns, and the technical aspects of leveraging this exciting new technology.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>King</last_name>
          <first_name>David Lee</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Services Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Topeka &amp;amp; Shawnee County Public Library and Publisher, davidleeking.com</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Murphy</last_name>
          <first_name>Joe</first_name>
          <job_title>Library Directions &amp;amp; Tech Trends Analyst. Director Library Futures.</job_title>
          <works_for>Library Future Innovative Interfaces, Yale Uni</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W8 &#x96; Searchers Academy</title>
      <description>Want to sharpen your web search skills? Find information in the real-time collaborative and social web? Learn from the experts? Join search veterans, speakers, and authors to learn the latest strategies and techniques for searching online. This fast-paced, newly updated, day-long event allows you to interact with the experts, who share their searching secrets and expertise as they focus on the most-current practices in the field of web research. There&#x2019;s always something new to be learned from these leading-edge panelists. Participants should have basic experience with web searching, but even searchers with an extensive searching background will find tips to polish and advance their skills and will come away with new resources and tools. Academy topics include the following:</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Bates</last_name>
          <first_name>Mary Ellen</first_name>
          <job_title>Principal</job_title>
          <works_for>Bates Information Services, Inc.</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Notess</last_name>
          <first_name>Greg</first_name>
          <job_title>Faculty &amp;amp; Graduate Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Montana State University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Price</last_name>
          <first_name>Gary</first_name>
          <job_title>Co-Founder</job_title>
          <works_for>INFODocket &amp;amp; FullTextReports</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Phelps</last_name>
          <first_name>Marcy</first_name>
          <job_title>President</job_title>
          <works_for>Phelps Research Inc. Author, Research on Main Street: Using the Web to Find Local Business and Market Information</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W9 &#x96; Web Managers Academy 3.0: Seamless Websites &amp;amp; Expanded Presence</title>
      <description>User expectations of what a good website is and does are higher than ever. Users expect high-quality information and services to be available to them whenever and wherever they are, be it via their desktop, mobile device, or via social media channels. Administrators are increasingly seeking both qualitative and quantitative data from libraries to justify expenditures and focus. How can library web managers satisfy all of these demands? This workshop explores ways to take your website to the next level, turning it from a menu that leads users into a disjointed set of content repositories and services to a unified service delivery platform which creates, deploys, and repurposes high-impact content and uses analytics to identify &#x201C;friction points&#x201D; on any website and in social media channels. Learn to deliver content and services to users beyond the library website through other channels such as mobile and social media. Get tips, techniques, and strategies to help create a seamless and &#x201C;frictionless&#x201D; web experience. Learn to create, deliver, and repurpose high-impact content. Know how to evaluate and measure the strengths and weaknesses of your website and social media and be prepared to positively face off with both users and stakeholders!</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Fichter</last_name>
          <first_name>Darlene</first_name>
          <job_title>GovInfo Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Saskatchewan Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Wisniewski</last_name>
          <first_name>Jeff</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Pittsburgh</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Breeding</last_name>
          <first_name>Marshall</first_name>
          <job_title>Independent Consultant and Founder of Library Technology Guides</job_title>
          <works_for>Founder of Library Technology Guides</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Cervone</last_name>
          <first_name>Frank</first_name>
          <job_title>Managing Partner</job_title>
          <works_for>Cervone and Associates</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W10 &#x96; Drupal: Start to Finish in a Day</title>
      <description>This full-day, intensive, hands-on workshop is for new and novice Drupal users. It covers Drupal 6 and 7 skills including installation, configuration, core functions, and theme development. This introductory workshop touches on most every aspect of the core Drupal framework:</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Carver</last_name>
          <first_name>Blake</first_name>
          <job_title>Owner</job_title>
          <works_for>LISHost.org</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Fitzpatrick</last_name>
          <first_name>Sean</first_name>
          <job_title>Drupal Developer</job_title>
          <works_for>LISHost.org</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W11 &#x96; Listening to the Customer</title>
      <description>This workshop discusses why listening to customers is so critical and then focuses in detail on who your customers are and segments them by use and reasons for use. It delves into the four categories of listening including solicited and structured methods (surveys, interviews, mystery shopping) as well as unsolicited and structured methods (complaints and compliments, suggestion/comment cards, comments and suggestions in surveys) as well as others. Joe Matthews uses examples from many different types of libraries to illustrate how using the &#x201C;customer&#x2019;s voice&#x201D; improves service and to show how important it is to involve staff in listening to the customer.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Matthews</last_name>
          <first_name>Joe</first_name>
          <job_title>Author</job_title>
          <works_for>Listening to the Voice of the Customer, JRM Consulting, Inc.</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W12 &#x96; Webcasting &amp;amp; Podcasting: Building Connections, Conversations, &amp;amp; Content on the Net</title>
      <description>This interactive workshop by experienced webcast and podcast producers covers the planning, running, and pre- and postproduction of webcasts and podcasts of NCompass Live. Based on the speakers' weekly NCompass Live episodes, the workshop illustrates how to broadcast live, record, and make available in both video and audio formats a program that can cover a variety of library topics ranging from children's services to services for the blind and visually impaired, to a monthly "Tech Talk" episode. Help the speakers build an episode of the show so you'll know how all the steps fit and how to build a program in your environment. Get all their tips and techniques as they share their secrets of success for the NCompass Live program.&#xA0;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Sauers</last_name>
          <first_name>Michael P</first_name>
          <job_title>Technology Innovation Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Technology &amp;amp; Access Services, Nebraska Library Commission</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Burns</last_name>
          <first_name>Christa</first_name>
          <job_title>Special Projects Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Nebraska Library Commission</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W13 &#x96; Designing Mobile Experiences</title>
      <description>Continuous access to information is a near reality. Smartphone and mobile devices are the tools that make it all possible. Providing content to these tools and devices presents interesting design and development challenges. Lost connections, limited battery power, smaller screens, touch interfaces&#x2014;these factors create a new way of thinking about web development and design. This workshop looks at trends in mobile interfaces, mobile sites versus mobile apps, emerging conventions for mobile design, best practices for mobile development, wizards, tools, and code templates for mobile site development. Come learn how to start creating mobile sites at your library and get a code walkthrough as well as a chance to build a sample web app.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Clark</last_name>
          <first_name>Jason A.</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Initiatives Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Head of Digital Access and Web Services, Montana State University Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Hill</last_name>
          <first_name>Nate</first_name>
          <job_title>Assistant Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Chattanooga Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W14 &#x96; Screencasting: Tips &amp;amp; Tricks for Fast &amp;amp; Easy Online Tutorials</title>
      <description>Online tutorials can be extremely time-intensive to create. Screencasts offer quicker ways to&#xA0; create informative tutorials that demonstrate online library resources or anything else on the web or your desktop. New tools make it quick and easy to create screencasts and host them online. Explore using free and fee software such as Jing, Camtasia Studio, and web-based services to quickly create online tutorials for your users. Compare hosting options at Screencast.com, YouTube, blip.tv, or Freescreencast. In addition to gathering proven tips, techniques, and tricks for quick screencast creation, see examples of advanced editing features such as call-outs, transitions, zooming, and highlights. Bring your own laptop to check out sites that are discussed. Show and tell the easy way!</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Notess</last_name>
          <first_name>Greg</first_name>
          <job_title>Faculty &amp;amp; Graduate Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Montana State University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W15 &#x96; Technology Planning: What's on Your Horizon?</title>
      <description>If you want to lead the pack, you need to be planning for lots of different technologies, challenges, and issues. Our leading thinker and practitioner challenges you to think about building strategies and plans for both near- and long-term technology challenges and opportunities. In this interactive workshop, Roy Tennant describes a variety of technologies (e.g., mobile computing, electronic books, data visualization, etc.), illustrates how they impact libraries, and supplies library examples where they exist. You&#x2019;ll leave not only with some tools for planning for technological change, but also with a sense of where things are now and where we are headed.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Tennant</last_name>
          <first_name>Roy</first_name>
          <job_title>Senior Program Officer</job_title>
          <works_for>Research, OCLC Online Computer Library Center, Inc.</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W16 &#x96; TIPS for Managing Tech &amp;amp; Workflow Changes in Libraries</title>
      <description>With rapidly changing technology and workflows, increased and morphing user demands, economic stress, and widely varied staff skill sets, library managers in every department and every type of library find themselves in a quandary without excellent and specific change management skills. This interactive workshop invites you to focus on the four TIPS of technology and workflow change management: Technology, Infrastructure, Planning, and Skills. The workshop addresses planning for managing technology change projects, with guidance and real-world exercises in project planning, workflow assessment, project implementation, critical reflection, and staff skill development. Leave this workshop with specific tools and structures that apply to projects underway, or being planned for the future, at your own library.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Harris</last_name>
          <first_name>Colleen S.</first_name>
          <job_title>Head of Access Services</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Tennessee &#x96; Chattanooga</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W17 &#x96; Streamlining Data for Cross-Platform Web Delivery</title>
      <description>With smartphones, the presentation of websites is expected to work more like one of the various mobile OS&#x2019;s native applications. With the demand on library web developers to produce app-like mobile sites, there is often a rush to get a site up without considering the importance of streamlining or even restructuring the data driving the websites. Additionally, content maintenance is required of any web site regardless of platform, so it becomes advantageous to pull content from other systems to decrease redundancy. This workshop highlights case studies from two universities, examines how each one is structuring its data for multiple web-based platforms, and discusses how to work toward making data more flexible so that content is delivered from single source points rather than duplicated for the individual delivery platform. It provides participants with an opportunity to discuss their data challenges with the presenters and peers facing similar issues, and provides guidance on approaches as well as tips to building more efficient data delivery.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Battles</last_name>
          <first_name>Jason J</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Office of Library Technology, University Libraries, The University of Alabama</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Vacek</last_name>
          <first_name>Rachel</first_name>
          <job_title>Head of Web Services</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Houston</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Watkins</last_name>
          <first_name>Sean</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Developer</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Houston</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W18 &#x96; Web Developers Boot Camp</title>
      <description>Are you a solo web developer with an interest in learning basic web scripting? A newbie thrown into your library web programming role because nobody else raised their hand? Somebody with a little more experience but always looking to improve your programming skills? This workshop is for you. Speakers work through the basics of web programming and highlight resources to continue learning. Their emphasis is on mashups and web services as a means to practice these skills. Featured topics include REST and Structured Data (e.g., JSON); common programming routines and functions; building simple video widgets with the YouTube API; mapping data with Google Maps; and learning how JavaScript (jQuery) and PHP work together to create advanced search mashups with the WorldCat API. Note: Attendees should bring a laptop to play along with the examples and have some familiarity with HTML and a scripting language.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Clark</last_name>
          <first_name>Jason A.</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Initiatives Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Head of Digital Access and Web Services, Montana State University Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Hollister</last_name>
          <first_name>Amanda</first_name>
          <job_title>Systems Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Broome Community College</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W19 &#x96; Handheld Librarians' Mobile Tech Tutorial</title>
      <description>This interactive and hands-on workshop provides a complete overview of mobile technologies, discusses the concept of the mobile revolution, and shares the potential applications to libraries. This tailored learning experience includes expert guest speakers presenting ideas originally shared at the online Handheld Librarian conferences. The workshop outlines the major mobile technologies available for libraries and exact methods for applying them with strategies for success. It focuses on interactive discussions enhanced by the mobile tools themselves and features immersive hands-on learning and playing to deliver specific take-aways that attendees can immediately apply to their libraries. Bring your laptop/notebook/ mobile device/tablet!</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Murphy</last_name>
          <first_name>Joe</first_name>
          <job_title>Library Directions &amp;amp; Tech Trends Analyst. Director Library Futures.</job_title>
          <works_for>Library Future Innovative Interfaces, Yale Uni</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Mairn</last_name>
          <first_name>Chad</first_name>
          <job_title>Information Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>St. Petersburg College</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>W20 &#x96; Implementing Technology Solutions in Libraries</title>
      <description>Get ready for a practical and concrete session filled with tangible tips that you can take back to your library and use to implement technology projects successfully. Learn about the important process of planning, implementing, and managing IT projects in libraries. The theme: Technology should never drive any IT project. Rather, technology should be a solution to help meet a need at the library; technology should support library staff so the library can better serve its customers. From the beginning, a project is defined out of a need at the library, based on the library&#x2019;s goals and plans&#x2014;ideally a technology plan. From there, solutions are explored, one is chosen and implemented, partnerships can be formed, and library service is enhanced. This is not just another session to help library staff members understand technology in their library&#x2014;this is designed to help library staff members find the right match for technology solutions to further the library&#x2019;s goals.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Knox</last_name>
          <first_name>Karen</first_name>
          <job_title>Associate Director and IT Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Rochester Hills Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Gaming &amp;amp; Gadgets Petting Zoo</title>
      <description>Join our gamers and gadget lovers for an evening of fun and playing. Bring your latest games and gadgets and try out each other&#x2019;s. See if you are a guitar hero, winning Wii bowler/golfer, or rank as a dancing DDR expert. Led by gamer/gadget gurus Aaron Schmidt, Amy Buckland, Royce Kitts, Erik Boekesteijn, and Jaap Van de Geer, this evening is filled with fun, networking, and, of course, learning and laughing. Refreshments included.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Boekesteijn</last_name>
          <first_name>Erik</first_name>
          <job_title>founder and director Doklab</job_title>
          <works_for>Doklab ShanachieTour</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Buckland</last_name>
          <first_name>Amy</first_name>
          <job_title>eScholarship</job_title>
          <works_for>ePublishing &amp;amp; Digitization Coordinator, McGill University Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Kitts</last_name>
          <first_name>Royce</first_name>
          <job_title>Education Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Washburn University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Geer</last_name>
          <first_name>Jaap Van de</first_name>
          <job_title>Delft Public Library</job_title>
          <works_for>D</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>OPENING KEYNOTE &#x97; Information &amp;amp; Learning for the Future</title>
      <description>Our distinguished thought leader, author, and practitioner looks at how the forces of change, and emerging waves of interest associated with these forces, inspire and invite us to imagine a future of learning that is as powerful as it is optimistic. By exploring play, innovation, and the cultivation of the imagination as cornerstones of learning, Brown shares his vision of learning for the future that is achievable, scalable, and one that grows along with the technology that fosters it and the people who engage with it. A new form of culture in which knowledge is seen as fluid and evolving is one in which Internet Librarians can excel and support learning with content, connections and conversations.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Brown</last_name>
          <first_name>John Seely</first_name>
          <job_title>Chief of Confusion; Visiting Scholar at USC; Independent  Co-Chairman of the Deloitte Center for the Edge &amp;amp; Author</job_title>
          <works_for>The New Culture of Learning</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Coffee Break</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A101 &#x96; Major Upcoming Mobile Trends &amp;amp; Location Applications</title>
      <description>O&#x2019;Dell, a veteran tech journalist, shares her view of the next major trends in mobile technology and explores emerging location-sharing and image-sharing technologies. This is a not-to-be missed session.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>O'Dell</last_name>
          <first_name>Jolie</first_name>
          <job_title>Technology Journalist</job_title>
          <works_for>Mashable.com</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A102 &#x96; QR Codes in Action</title>
      <description>Engage, entertain, and enrich your community with local history photographs and snippets of information by developing mobile tours that connect places and things to collections. This panel shares their QR code secrets for promoting, browsing, and connecting; mobilizing stacks; and more.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Donahue</last_name>
          <first_name>Tim</first_name>
          <job_title>Instruction Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Montana State University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Clark</last_name>
          <first_name>Jason A.</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Initiatives Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Head of Digital Access and Web Services, Montana State University Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Kane</last_name>
          <first_name>Danielle</first_name>
          <job_title>Research Librarian for Emerging Technologies and Service Innovation</job_title>
          <works_for>University of California, Irvine</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Gurganus</last_name>
          <first_name>Alison Steinberg</first_name>
          <job_title>Online Services &amp;amp; Instruction Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>San Diego Mesa College</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Fichter</last_name>
          <first_name>Darlene</first_name>
          <job_title>GovInfo Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Saskatchewan Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Avery</last_name>
          <first_name>Cheryl</first_name>
          <job_title>Archivist</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Saskatchewan</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A103 &#x96; Next Big Trends: Near Field Communication &amp;amp; Interactive Picture Books</title>
      <description>This session focuses on collections and services, the areas of influence for libraries. Hear about two major technologies that are disrupting collections and services for libraries. Interactive ebooks (books? games? apps?) are going to be the next major wave in mobile content. Near field communication (NFC) will revolutionize how we connect and transfer information.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Caserotti</last_name>
          <first_name>Gretchen</first_name>
          <job_title>Assistant Director for Public Services</job_title>
          <works_for>Darien Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Yarmey</last_name>
          <first_name>Kristen</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>The University of Scranton Weinberg Memorial Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>McHugh</last_name>
          <first_name>Sheli</first_name>
          <job_title>Cataloging and Metadata Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>The University of Scranton Weinberg Memorial Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A104 &#x96; Mobile Landscape, Cool Tools, &amp;amp; the Future</title>
      <description>This session looks at the mobile landscape, highlights some cool tools for the mobile world, looks at some research about what&#x2019;s happening and will happen in the future. It is filled with insights and ideas for how you can plan and implement mobile strategies and practices for your environment.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Helfer</last_name>
          <first_name>Doris Small</first_name>
          <job_title>Sciences</job_title>
          <works_for>Social Sciences and Humanities Librarian, Oviatt Library, California State University, Northridge</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Woodley</last_name>
          <first_name>Mary</first_name>
          <job_title>Collection Development Coordinator</job_title>
          <works_for>California State University, Northridge</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Altman</last_name>
          <first_name>Elizabeth</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Services Coordinator</job_title>
          <works_for>California State University, Northridge</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Thomas</last_name>
          <first_name>Lisa Carlucci</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Southern Connecticut State University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Wisniewski</last_name>
          <first_name>Jeff</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Pittsburgh</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A105 &#x96; Developing a Mobile Presence: Mobile Web, Usability, and Devices</title>
      <description>This session covers developing a presence for mobile websites, considerations for mobile usability, and designing programs for a presence on mobile devices as well as portals. Hear about an experiment using iPads at public libraries in Denmark. Learn about storyboarding and scenario prototyping for mastering mobile usability. And explore how designing a mobile website might be a bit simpler than you thought.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Fjord</last_name>
          <first_name>Esben</first_name>
          <job_title>Head of Development</job_title>
          <works_for>Gladsaxe Public Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Hill</last_name>
          <first_name>Nate</first_name>
          <job_title>Assistant Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Chattanooga Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Shields</last_name>
          <first_name>Joel</first_name>
          <job_title>Systems Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Washington Research Library Consortium (WRLC)</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A106 &#x96; E-Collections and E-Devices</title>
      <description>Hear how the University of Nevada&#x2013;Reno library set up an Apple Store-inspired e-reader bar to help patrons explore various handheld devices. Maslyukova addresses the questions of how to manage expectations of clients and provide access to a growing number of mobile products in The World Bank.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Kurt</last_name>
          <first_name>Lisa</first_name>
          <job_title>Emerging Technologies Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Nevada, Reno</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Colegrove</last_name>
          <first_name>Tod</first_name>
          <job_title>Head of DeLaMare Science &amp;amp; Engineering Library</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Nevada, Reno</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Maslyukova</last_name>
          <first_name>Elena</first_name>
          <job_title>Information Officer</job_title>
          <works_for>The World Bank</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Exhibit Hall Grand Opening Reception</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Coffee Break</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B101 &#x96; 20 Steps to Creating Web-Based Library Services</title>
      <description>This session is for those libraries struggling to provide innovative technology services with little resources to devote to staff, software, or hardware. The bright and shiny tech projects we see sometimes seem impossible to implement in smaller, poorer, and/or under-technology-staffed libraries. But we too can offer excellent online services to our users! Take advantage of the quick and free services that any library can add to its website with minimal time or expertise. This session highlights 20 easy steps libraries can take to improve their websites with ease. If your library hasn&#x2019;t yet implemented the newest and greatest technologies on its website but wants to, join us for lots of tips and tricks.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Houghton</last_name>
          <first_name>Sarah</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>San Rafael Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B102 &#x96; Improving Your Website With Google Analytics' Statistics</title>
      <description>Web metrics help us improve services by revealing users&#x2019; behaviors on the website. Ho shows how to use Google analytics to see the most popular webpages, how people arrive at a page, and where people go after viewing a page. This data can point out pages that are important to update, if the page is working as expected and ways to make sure people find your pages. Wisniewski shows how to segment website traffic to do some deep diving into understanding users&#x2019; behaviors. He discusses goals and how they aren&#x2019;t just for businesses selling a product but can help libraries make better website processes.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Ho</last_name>
          <first_name>SuHui</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of California, San Diego</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Wisniewski</last_name>
          <first_name>Jeff</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Pittsburgh</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B103 &#x96; It's All About the Customer!</title>
      <description>UC Irvine Libraries recognize that a library&#x2019;s website is the busiest service point. Learn how to apply time-tested customer service concepts to an online environment and assess their impact. Explore customer service options from easy to implement to bigger projects that involve more investment. Colegrove discusses the best way to serve users who have a heavy reliance on Google as their first choice for research. Learn from his pioneering work on what&#x2019;s working and what isn&#x2019;t as he shares results of trials utilizing different approaches to marketing library e-resources at the point of need. Find out what he discovered about printed bit.ly links, QR codes on library materials, and using targeted advertising on Google and Facebook. Take a peek at recent changes in Google AdWords API that may be of use to libraries.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Ferry</last_name>
          <first_name>Kristine</first_name>
          <job_title>Head</job_title>
          <works_for>Access Services, UC Irvine Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Johnson</last_name>
          <first_name>Cynthia</first_name>
          <job_title>Head of Reference</job_title>
          <works_for>UC Irvine Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Palmer</last_name>
          <first_name>Cathy</first_name>
          <job_title>Head of Education &amp;amp; Outreach</job_title>
          <works_for>UC Irvine Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Colegrove</last_name>
          <first_name>Tod</first_name>
          <job_title>Head of DeLaMare Science &amp;amp; Engineering Library</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Nevada, Reno</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B104 &#x96; Using the Cloud to Power Library Sites &amp;amp; Services</title>
      <description>Learn about the ups and downs of implementing hosted solutions in libraries, the benefits to staff and patrons, and what helps a project succeed. Starting off with a public library case study, find out why VPL turned to hosted and implemented Bibliocommons to add social media features to the catalogue, and rolled out LibGuides. Many academic libraries have adopted the LibGuides platform but how well is it working? The Miami U team decided to find out how usable LibGuides are. They looked at the placement of the guides in the website and organization schemes to discover what is intuitive, comprehensible, learnable, and useful. They report the findings of their comprehensive usability study and share a set of best practices for LibGuide design and layout based on their findings.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Castell</last_name>
          <first_name>Christina de</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Resources &amp;amp; Technology, Vancouver Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Walker</last_name>
          <first_name>Cecily</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Vancouver Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Revelle</last_name>
          <first_name>Andrew</first_name>
          <job_title>Social Sciences Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Miami University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Michel</last_name>
          <first_name>Jason</first_name>
          <job_title>User Experience Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Miami University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Sullivan</last_name>
          <first_name>Elizabeth</first_name>
          <job_title>Psychology Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Miami University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B105 &#x96; Drupal vs. WordPress vs. Joomla Smackdown</title>
      <description>Which open source content management system (CMS) is right for you (or your library)? Learn all about what makes WordPress, Drupal, and Joomla the leaders in the open source CMS space. Speakers cover the present and future of Drupal, WordPress, and Joomla and expose the strengths and weaknesses of the systems. They help you decide which CMS is best for certain types of applications such as personal blogs, library websites, and other applications.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Carver</last_name>
          <first_name>Blake</first_name>
          <job_title>Owner</job_title>
          <works_for>LISHost.org</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Levine</last_name>
          <first_name>Kendra K.</first_name>
          <job_title>Librarian At Large</job_title>
          <works_for>L</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B106 &#x96; Tips on Redesigning Library Sites</title>
      <description>Epstein looks at ways librarians who partner with external stakeholders on campus can communicate the unique needs of the library website through conversations,&#xA0; collaborations, and negotiations. Franklyn describes a library website redesign and shares insights into using Drupal as the content management system and the value of usability studies. The Marin County Free Library team discusses taking a website from mess to success in a challenging environment with comments on new leadership, limited time, diverse staff in 10 locations, library brand in flux, and a commitment to incorporating a full-scale social media integration. Our practitioners share tips on redesigns as well as lessons learned on how to work effectively with staff and the public.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Epstein</last_name>
          <first_name>Michael</first_name>
          <job_title>Electronic Resources Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of San Diego, Copley Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Franklyn</last_name>
          <first_name>Virginia</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Developer</job_title>
          <works_for>Pikes Peak Library District</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Foust</last_name>
          <first_name>Amanda</first_name>
          <job_title>Electronic Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Marin County Free Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Jonsson</last_name>
          <first_name>Anna</first_name>
          <job_title>Library Assistant</job_title>
          <works_for>Marin County Free Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Magnus</last_name>
          <first_name>Julie</first_name>
          <job_title>Head of Reference</job_title>
          <works_for>Marin County Free Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Exhibit Hall Grand Opening Reception</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Coffee Break</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C101 &#x96; Super Searcher Spectacular Secrets!</title>
      <description>One of our most popular sessions returns to share the latest secrets and strategies for web research. Our well-known super searcher and host of Searchers Academy provides an up-dated-to-the-minute and jam-packed-with-valuabletips-and-tools talk about searching the web more effectively. You don&#x2019;t need to be an expert to use these tips and techniques, but even long-time researchers will learn something new.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Bates</last_name>
          <first_name>Mary Ellen</first_name>
          <job_title>Principal</job_title>
          <works_for>Bates Information Services, Inc.</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C102 &#x96; Advances in Discovery Engines &amp;amp; Services</title>
      <description>Notess reports on current pros and cons of discovery engines and Breeding discusses the new generation of discovery products emerging to replace older-generation library catalogs. The genre of discovery products continues to advance, with ever more powerful capabilities. Many now include the ability to rapidly search not only the content of traditional library catalogs, but to also offer much deeper search&#xA0; capabilities including the individual articles represented in a library&#x2019;s subscriptions. These products continue to expand indexing and full-text coverage of both articles and books. Come hear the latest news about developments in search and content delivery products.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Notess</last_name>
          <first_name>Greg</first_name>
          <job_title>Faculty &amp;amp; Graduate Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Montana State University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Breeding</last_name>
          <first_name>Marshall</first_name>
          <job_title>Independent Consultant and Founder of Library Technology Guides</job_title>
          <works_for>Founder of Library Technology Guides</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C103 &#x96; 21st Century Book Recommendation Engines</title>
      <description>Is &#x201C;readers&#x2019; advisory&#x201D; just so last century? What are the models for reading recommendations that work? Are libraries different than retailers? How do you build reading communities? What are the best practices for building trust in your recommendations and reviews? What are the dynamics of the local market for public libraries and is there enough to differentiate local library service from the retail model? What tools and resources can be provided in context to readers? Can we add the author and illustrator dimension to reader choice? Hear from three experienced and creative suppliers about new techniques to crowdsource readers&#x2019; advisory services and their experience with new models for libraries.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Abram</last_name>
          <first_name>Stephen</first_name>
          <job_title>Principal</job_title>
          <works_for>Lighthouse Consulting Inc.</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Jefferson</last_name>
          <first_name>Beth</first_name>
          <job_title>CEO</job_title>
          <works_for>Bibliocommons</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Spalding</last_name>
          <first_name>Tim</first_name>
          <job_title>CEO</job_title>
          <works_for>LibraryThing</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Johnson</last_name>
          <first_name>Scott</first_name>
          <job_title>President</job_title>
          <works_for>CEO, ChiliFresh.com</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C104 &#x96; Best Betas for Learning &amp;amp; Navigating</title>
      <description>New beta releases of interest to info pros and library users continuously become available from well-known providers as well as new technology providers. Since it can be very time-consuming to learn about new beta releases, determine how to use them, and evaluate them, Price discusses some of the latest beta releases and shares some of the tools and techniques he uses to locate these resources. This popular speaker never disappoints in highlighting insights and tools anyone can use!</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Price</last_name>
          <first_name>Gary</first_name>
          <job_title>Co-Founder</job_title>
          <works_for>INFODocket &amp;amp; FullTextReports</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C105 &#x96; Top Tips for Turning Information Into Insights</title>
      <description>In the age of Google and information overload, it&#x2019;s no longer a matter of what or how much information you have &#x2014; it&#x2019;s what you do with it. The first presentation demonstrates how to use advanced features of Google to find quality results faster.&#xA0; Phelps provides tips and techniques for creating products and services that make information useful to your clients, while increasing your value.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Bonato</last_name>
          <first_name>Sarah r</first_name>
          <job_title>Reference/Research Librarian and Collection Development Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Browne</last_name>
          <first_name>Melanie</first_name>
          <job_title>Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Digital Research, Maple Leaf Foods</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Phelps</last_name>
          <first_name>Marcy</first_name>
          <job_title>President</job_title>
          <works_for>Phelps Research Inc. Author, Research on Main Street: Using the Web to Find Local Business and Market Information</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C106 &#x96; Browser Battles: Next Generation of Browser Wars</title>
      <description>Internet Explorer (IE) beat out Mozilla to win the browser wars of yore, but now IE and Firefox are seeing increased competition from Google&#x2019;s Chrome, Apple&#x2019;s Safari, and new browsers for smartphones, tablets, and e-readers. Meanwhile, IE and Firefox have launched new versions with significant&#xA0; changes.&#xA0; Come explore these web browser changes, unique features, search options, privacy issues, and more. Learn the impact for both users and web designers.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Notess</last_name>
          <first_name>Greg</first_name>
          <job_title>Faculty &amp;amp; Graduate Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Montana State University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Exhibit Hall Grand Opening Reception</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Coffee Break</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D101 &#x96; Training Is Not Learning?</title>
      <description>Library culture is training-focused. We talk about teaching our patrons to fish rather than handing them a fillet, but when it comes to our own learning, we want the seafood platter set in front of us. Library &#x201C;trainers&#x201D; Newman, Farrington, and Sheehan discuss the need for cultural change in libraries while sharing their own successes and not-so successes.&#xA0; Clasper describes the training program designed to keep the county libraries&#x2019; staff current with the technology they use every day. The program incorporated workshops, webinars, multimedia, games, and a web-based online learning center, where staff engaged their colleagues in a professional development community.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Sheehan</last_name>
          <first_name>Kate</first_name>
          <job_title>Open Source Implementation Coordinator</job_title>
          <works_for>Bibliomation ALA TechSource Blogger</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Newman</last_name>
          <first_name>Bobbi L.</first_name>
          <job_title>Consultant</job_title>
          <works_for>writer, Librarian by Day</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Farrington</last_name>
          <first_name>Polly-Alida</first_name>
          <job_title>Consultant &amp;amp;  Trainer</job_title>
          <works_for>PA Farrington Associates</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Clasper</last_name>
          <first_name>Emily</first_name>
          <job_title>System Operations and Training Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Suffolk Cooperative Library System</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D102 &#x96; From Training to Learning: Strategic Community Conversations</title>
      <description>Supporting communities that are vastly different in terms of geography, culture, interest, and practice requires that libraries truly learn about these communities. Calgary Public Library is supporting librarians to self-identify their personal learning requirements, develop individual learning plans, and ultimately enhance the organizational ability to be highly visible and active participants in the work of our communities.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>MacKenzie</last_name>
          <first_name>Nancy</first_name>
          <job_title>Customer Service Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Calgary Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Hardy</last_name>
          <first_name>Lisa</first_name>
          <job_title>Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>West Sector, Calgary Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D103 &#x96; Transliteracy &amp;amp; 21st-Century Skills for Library Users</title>
      <description>Digital literacy, media literacy, information literacy, 21st-century literacy, and other new literacies are all included in transliteracy. Newman, Hollier and Hamilton cover the importance of transliteracy and libraries&#x2019; role in supporting patrons&#x2019; development of these skills. Koerber looks at BPL&#x2019;s Learning for Life Online, a free, ongoing online learning community platform that helps users develop a framework for a lifetime of learning and exploration. Based on four powerful tools &#x2014; a WordPress site, Twitter, Facebook and the library&#x2019;s social discovery catalog &#x2014; the program has been a learning experience for the library and patrons, and you&#x2019;ll come away with a checklist to start online patron training programs at your library.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Newman</last_name>
          <first_name>Bobbi L.</first_name>
          <job_title>Consultant</job_title>
          <works_for>writer, Librarian by Day</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Hollier</last_name>
          <first_name>Jamie</first_name>
          <job_title>Owner</job_title>
          <works_for>Anneal, Inc Project Manager with PLA, Board Member for DPLA</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Hamilton</last_name>
          <first_name>Matthew</first_name>
          <job_title>IT Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Denver Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Koerber</last_name>
          <first_name>Jennifer</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Boston Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D104 &#x96; iLibrarian: Virtual, iPads &amp;amp; Mobile Devices</title>
      <description>Miller shares IUPUI&#x2019;s experience using iPads and mobile devices to teach undergrads, as well as preliminary findings of a study of student learning and perceptions of mobile resources for library instruction and access. Applications include Popplet, iBrainstorm, GoodReader, Dropbox, and others. The University of La Verne team gives a &#x201C;how-to&#x201D; presentation illustrating how regional campus administration collaborated with the university library to design and implement virtual delivery of library research instruction to 5,000 distance learners using Acrobat Adobe Connect and Business Skype.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Miller</last_name>
          <first_name>Willie</first_name>
          <job_title>Assistant Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Indiana University-Purdue University, Indianapolis</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Gordon</last_name>
          <first_name>Linda</first_name>
          <job_title>Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of La Verne</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Vincent</last_name>
          <first_name>Kitt</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Central Coast Regional Campus, University of La Verne</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Swarm</last_name>
          <first_name>Darryl</first_name>
          <job_title>Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of La Verne</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D105 &#x96; Blackboard Learn: Partnering to Integrate Resources</title>
      <description>New partnerships and collaboration on a campus migration to Blackboard Learn allowed UH Libraries to fully integrate library resources and successfully streamline and manage the content. This presentation discusses the conversations and partnerships between the library and campus instructional designers, lessons learned from being on the Blackboard implementation team, the technical aspects of how UH libraries streamlined the delivery of content, and the future implications for the library team that will manage the content.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Dryden</last_name>
          <first_name>Anita R.</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital &amp;amp; Web Projects Fellow</job_title>
          <works_for>Unviersity of Houston Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Gola</last_name>
          <first_name>Christina H.</first_name>
          <job_title>Head of Library Instruction</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Houston Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D106 &#x96; Instruction Goes Viral With Videos</title>
      <description>Both of these libraries learned valuable lessons about using video for teaching and tutorials. Steinberg covers the types of tutorials turning heads; software (paid and free) used to create them; scripting and rehearsal techniques for smooth and easy listening; website, course management system (CMS), or LibGuide placement; and where to find tutorials already created and ready for you to use! Thornley describes a semester-long assignment revolving around video dissemination</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Gurganus</last_name>
          <first_name>Alison Steinberg</first_name>
          <job_title>Online Services &amp;amp; Instruction Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>San Diego Mesa College</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Thornley</last_name>
          <first_name>Amy</first_name>
          <job_title>Education Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Miami University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Exhibit Hall Grand Opening Reception</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Coffee Break</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>E101 &#x96; Changing the Story: The California Campaign for Strong School Libraries</title>
      <description>The California Campaign for Strong School Libraries is a public awareness campaign that seeks to inform the public and policymakers on the importance of a strong school library in increasing student academic achievement. The campaign promotes the new Model School Library Standards and works to &#x201C;change the story&#x201D; of what a school is. California School Library Association&#x2019;s Siminitus and Williams showcase a number of major outreach efforts including an audio journal; bus ads; Illustrators Galore @ LIBRARY STORE; leveraging library vendors as advocates; plus how to design and offer their free, online tutorial for teens, &#x201C;Tools2Create: Summer 2.0 Fun.&#x201D;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Siminitus</last_name>
          <first_name>Jackie</first_name>
          <job_title>VP</job_title>
          <works_for>Communication, California School Library Association</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Williams</last_name>
          <first_name>Connie</first_name>
          <job_title>Chair</job_title>
          <works_for>California Campaign for Strong School Libraries, California School Library Association</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>E102 &#x96; Ebooks in Libraries and Schools-How to Increase Access and Improve the User Experience</title>
      <description>Ebook circulation at libraries and schools is taking off, having increased 200% in 2010. Discover from Brian Gurewitz, an ebook industry insider, how you can take advantage of this surge in popularity as he introduces the latest enhancements from OverDrive.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Gurewitz</last_name>
          <first_name>Brian</first_name>
          <job_title>Director of Content Sales</job_title>
          <works_for>OverDrive</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>E104 &#x96; Critical Thinking About Online Sources- Liven Up Those Lessons!</title>
      <description>Do your students know the difference between a discussion list and a wiki? How should they regard a newspaper article that is also a blog entry? Getting students to think critically about the range of resources they encounter on the web can be tough! So bring your lesson ideas, because in this actively participatory session, Bergson-Michelson and Seroff take on the challenge to develop more effective and exciting lessons that help teach students to identify what they are accessing online.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Bergson-Michleson</last_name>
          <first_name>Tasha</first_name>
          <job_title>Instructional and Programming Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Castilleja School</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Seroff</last_name>
          <first_name>Jole</first_name>
          <job_title>Director of Library and Information Services</job_title>
          <works_for>Castilleja School</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>E103 &#x96; Implementing Student Eportfolios</title>
      <description>Should your school consider implementing student eportfolios? How can you as a librarian be a part of the process? This session explores different avenues schools have taken to incorporate eportfolios into their curriculum. Geiger and Arriaga outline the essential elements of an eportfolio as well as hosting options such as Google sites. Join them as they share their experiences and lessons learned while implementing eportfolios.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Geiger</last_name>
          <first_name>Susan</first_name>
          <job_title>Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Moreau Catholic High School AISL, BAYNET, BASIL Past President</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Arriaga</last_name>
          <first_name>Anne</first_name>
          <job_title>Head Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Moreau Catholic High School</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>E105 &#x96; Point-of-Need Library and Research Instruction- Meeting Students "Where They Are"</title>
      <description>Teaching library and research instruction&#x2014;essential skills such as basic research, source evaluation, digital citizenship, avoiding plagiarism&#x2014;is vitally important. Students need to learn and retain these skills now more than ever, but it seems the school schedule gets tighter and tighter. In this session, hear how Tong and Daniel have revamped their program to provide skills instruction at the point of need in the &#x201C;location&#x201D; best suited to the situation. Learn from their successes (and mistakes!) as they discovered what skills to teach face-to-face, or as interactive, online modules. They also discuss how the library staff has integrated with the 9th grade history&#xA0; curriculum to provide specific, hands-on research instruction.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Tong</last_name>
          <first_name>Deb</first_name>
          <job_title>Upper School Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Columbus Academy</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Daniel</last_name>
          <first_name>Diane</first_name>
          <job_title>Upper School Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Columbus Academy</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>E106 &#x96; Research Gone Green</title>
      <description>Learn from high school librarians Dettling and Gorman how to transform the student research paper into a project that utilizes absolutely no paper! With the use of a digital notebook, such as Evernote, teach students to take notes, gather research, and effectively organize their information in a paperless format, all accessible from any computer&#x2014;a laptop at home, a desktop at school, or a mobile device such as an iPad, iPhone, Android, or BlackBerry. Then learn how to use Turnitin.com to not only collect electronic versions of student work, but also to assess and provide descriptive feedback at both the formative and summative stages. Lisa and Toni show how to use technology to get students enthusiastic about the research process and to support your school&#x2019;s Green Initiatives.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Dettling</last_name>
          <first_name>Lisa</first_name>
          <job_title>Head Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Adlai E. Stevenson High School</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Gorman</last_name>
          <first_name>Toni</first_name>
          <job_title>Associate Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Adlai E. Stevenson High School</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Exhibit Hall Grand Opening Reception</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>OPENING KEYNOTE &#x97; Libraries and Learning Communities</title>
      <description>Rainie discusses the Project's latest research about how people use the internet, smart phones, and tablet computers to get, create, and share information. The new media environment is a Petri Dish for community formation as every book, every blog, and every Facebook feed can foster group engagement. Join our popular speaker as he explores how libraries can serve those who are creating new kinds of communities and enriching traditional groups.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Rainie</last_name>
          <first_name>Lee</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Pew Research Center's Internet Project Author of the book "Networked: The New Social Operating System"</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Coffe Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A201 &#x96; Ebooks: Putting the Issues on the Table</title>
      <description>Our knowledgeable panel of experienced practitioners points out the key issues and challenges for all types of libraries as book formats and technologies are changing. Get the lay of the landscape in this interactive and insightful session.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Newman</last_name>
          <first_name>Bobbi L.</first_name>
          <job_title>Consultant</job_title>
          <works_for>writer, Librarian by Day</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Houghton</last_name>
          <first_name>Sarah</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>San Rafael Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Affelt</last_name>
          <first_name>Amy</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Database Research, Compass Lexecon</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Ward</last_name>
          <first_name>Faith</first_name>
          <job_title>Lower Division Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Garrison Forest School</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A202 &#x96; Ebooks &amp;amp; the Future of Publishing, Lending, Learning</title>
      <description>Hear from our panel of publishers about their ebook strategies and plans for the future.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Bowers</last_name>
          <first_name>David</first_name>
          <job_title>VP</job_title>
          <works_for>Global Business Development, Oxford University Press</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Abram</last_name>
          <first_name>Stephen</first_name>
          <job_title>Principal</job_title>
          <works_for>Lighthouse Consulting Inc.</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A203 &#x96; Talk About: Ebook Preservation</title>
      <description>Hear a publisher, librarian and ebook aggregator look at the issues and challenges around ebook preservation. They share research, explain the concepts, and their perspectives about the issues, responsibilities and open-questions they have.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Polanka</last_name>
          <first_name>Sue</first_name>
          <job_title>Head of Reference and Instruction</job_title>
          <works_for>Wright State University Libraries No Shelf Required</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Breen</last_name>
          <first_name>Ken</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>eBook Products, EBSCOhost</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Janke</last_name>
          <first_name>Rolf</first_name>
          <job_title>VP/Publisher</job_title>
          <works_for>SAGE Reference</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Networking Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A204 &#x96; Talk About: Ebooks, Users, &amp;amp; Library Workflow</title>
      <description>How libraries can acquire ebooks within their existing workflows has sometimes been a barrier to ebook adoption. In 2011, ebrary and YBP announced an integrated solution for selecting titles on the basis of patron demand. This panel addresses user-driven and other ebook models that integrate into the workflow and support loans.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Barnes</last_name>
          <first_name>Matt</first_name>
          <job_title>VP of Marketing</job_title>
          <works_for>ebrary</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Nauman</last_name>
          <first_name>Matt</first_name>
          <job_title>Baker &amp;amp; Taylor</job_title>
          <works_for>YBP Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Thomas</last_name>
          <first_name>Lisa Carlucci</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Southern Connecticut State University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A205 &#x96; Ebook Research &amp;amp; Experiments</title>
      <description>There&#x2019;s a print copy on the shelf, and an online link in the catalogue. Which do our users choose? Two medium-sized Canadian universities tested this with the Canadian Electronic Library, a collection of 8,000 backlisted Canadian ebooks held by most Canadian research libraries, and acquired through a national site licensing consortium. Using online access statistics and print circulation data, they compared use of the collection in both formats and examined trends. Hear their interesting results! SPL embarked on an experiment to lend more than 100 preloaded e-readers to the public, thanks to a grant from the state library, along with Friends of the Library funding. Partnering with Barnes &amp;amp; Noble for devices, content and training, a win-win collaborative community project, speakers share their learnings about implementing e-reader circulation including staff and user training, ebook selection, circulation procedures, project assessment, and more.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Jacobs</last_name>
          <first_name>Pamela</first_name>
          <job_title>Liaison/Collection Assessment Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Brock University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Rodgers</last_name>
          <first_name>Wendy</first_name>
          <job_title>Humanities Research Liaison Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Memorial University of Newfoundland</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Davis</last_name>
          <first_name>Denise</first_name>
          <job_title>Deputy Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Sacramento Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Calhoun</last_name>
          <first_name>Amy</first_name>
          <job_title>Virtual Branch Coordinator</job_title>
          <works_for>Virtual Branch, Sacramento Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Coffe Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B201 &#x96; UX Tools of the Trade</title>
      <description>Join our user experience (UX) expert and hear about UX tools that you can use in your environment to gather information on user perceptions of your websites, to understand how easy they feel your sites are to use, and to see how these perceptions change over time. Our speaker shares tips and techniques for user experience design and more.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Etches</last_name>
          <first_name>Amanda</first_name>
          <job_title>Head</job_title>
          <works_for>Discovery &amp;amp; Access, University of Guelph</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B202 &#x96; Building a Single User Experience</title>
      <description>The modern library web environment consists of multiple content sources and applications that perform essential functions that often overlap and could potentially create a fractured user experience. For example, content in a library&#x2019;s Drupal website may be replicated in LibGuides or WordPress blogs. Search functionality in a discovery platform may be replicated in a federated search tool or the ILS OPAC. This presentation provides tips, tackles technical and political challenges to building a single web experience for users, discusses solutions and use of APIs (application programming interfaces), provides concrete examples, and more.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Battles</last_name>
          <first_name>Jason J</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Office of Library Technology, University Libraries, The University of Alabama</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Vacek</last_name>
          <first_name>Rachel</first_name>
          <job_title>Head of Web Services</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Houston</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>McHale</last_name>
          <first_name>Nina</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Developer</job_title>
          <works_for>Digital Services, Arapahoe Library District</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B203 &#x96; Tools for Improving UX</title>
      <description>This panel of experienced practitioners focuses on time saving tools. The first presentation discusses how Google Apps helps resource-thin libraries provide key services such as email, calendaring and shared documentation for workflow without the cost of servers and IT staff as well as an innovative and helpful tool for librarians from larger institutions who need to find quick ways to create wikis and shared documentation, forms and shared spreadsheets, informal surveys, and more. Hill provides tips and techniques for effective user interface design.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Dene</last_name>
          <first_name>Jezmynne</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Portneuf District Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Vecchione</last_name>
          <first_name>Amy</first_name>
          <job_title>Assistant Professor/Digital Access Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Head Digital Access Team, Digital Access, Boise State University Idaho Library Associaton</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Hill</last_name>
          <first_name>Nate</first_name>
          <job_title>Assistant Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Chattanooga Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Networking Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B204 &#x96; Community Endorses Online 11:1</title>
      <description>This session showcases one of the busiest libraries in the nation. While 10-million-plus people walk through KCLS&#x2019;s doors each year to circulate 22 million items, its catalog and web hits combined total over 115 million visits. Driven by usability testing, KCLS developed a new graphic user interface for the recently implemented Evergreen OPAC. Staff are working cooperatively with other libraries on open source development of its Mobile and Kid&#x2019;s Catalog. Additionally, KCLS has added Boopsie to expand mobile offerings. Its Booktalk blog has over 60 contributing librarians using a decentralized model for maximum staff participation. YouTube holds over 500 instruction and informational videos, including Tell Me a Story featuring songs and rhymes by KCLS children&#x2019;s librarians. KCLS updates its Facebook page almost daily and &#x201C;tweets&#x201D; 20-30 times a week. In an effort to increase ebook circulation, it negotiated distribution of KCLS promotional materials at NOOK kiosks with the seven Barnes &amp;amp; Noble stores in its district. Focusing on internal communications, KCLS launched a new intranet using SharePoint under the themes Search, Share, and Collaborate. KCLS speakers share tips and tricks you can take home and implement in your environment!</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Siers</last_name>
          <first_name>Denise</first_name>
          <job_title>Director of Public Services</job_title>
          <works_for>King County Library System</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Falgout</last_name>
          <first_name>Melissa</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>King County Library System</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Wasserman</last_name>
          <first_name>David</first_name>
          <job_title>Online Services Coordinator</job_title>
          <works_for>King County Library System</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B205 &#x96; Designing for Optimal UX</title>
      <description>In this session we'll look at a some emerging library service models and some unusual types of library facilities.&#xA0; As libraries make a shift to collecting and distributing more digital content, library buildings need to change to reflect a new program.&#xA0; Is your library ready to embrace this kind of change?</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Hill</last_name>
          <first_name>Nate</first_name>
          <job_title>Assistant Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Chattanooga Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Noll</last_name>
          <first_name>Chris</first_name>
          <job_title>Noll &amp;amp; Tam Architects</job_title>
          <works_for>N</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Coffe Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C201 &#x96; Creating Web 2.0 Apps With SharePoint</title>
      <description>This presentation covers how libraries can use the out-of-the-box features of Microsoft&#x2019;s SharePoint to create Web 2.0 tools for conversation and collaboration. Using actual examples from the Sandia Technical Library&#x2019;s internal and customerfacing SharePoint websites, the talk gives a brief demonstration of how librarians can utilize SharePoint to offer library wikis, blogs, social tagging and cataloging, user surveys, newsfeeds, discussion boards, ratings and recommendations, video sharing, and more, all without the need for HTML or other coding skills.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Pollock</last_name>
          <first_name>Danielle</first_name>
          <job_title>Technical Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Sandia National Laboratories</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C202 &#x96; Drupal to the Next Level</title>
      <description>Based on its CMS review and the successful implementation of Drupal for the Advanced Technology Solar Telescope (presented at IL2007), the NSO decided to migrate all its other websites into Drupal as well. This session tracks that migration project, starting with new hardware identification; the realization that outside help was needed and partnering with the Cherry Hill Company; seeing where implementation was different (such as multisite versus single site) and where it was the same; noting configuration and module information; and sharing lessons learned from the project.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Kneale</last_name>
          <first_name>Ruth A</first_name>
          <job_title>Systems Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>ATST, National Solar Observatory</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Gordon</last_name>
          <first_name>Cary</first_name>
          <job_title>The Cherry Hill Company</job_title>
          <works_for>T</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C203 &#x96; Knowledge Management (KM) &amp;amp; Library Services</title>
      <description>Learn how librarians are using their expertise to develop connections within their organizations that deliver value by meeting the needs of internal and external customers. Discover how you can implement KM initiatives in your organization using existing tools and creative problem solving. Internal knowledge sharing, information silos and developing products that integrate internal and external data which vendors can&#x2019;t duplicate create added value for attorneys, managers, directors, and other professionals. The first talk provides tips on how to start small, market your successes, and build on those successes for larger-scale initiatives, discusses how to define KM in a way that fits your organizational culture and mission, which, in turn, sets realistic expectations of what KM&#xA0; can and&#xA0; cannot achieve. The Boeing team describes their robust KM strategy, which included modifying an existing ILS to be used as an institutional repository for internal Boeing documentation, partnering with internal groups to build communities around pertinent content, and integrating with Boeing Enterprise Search and Boeing Enterprise KM. Learn to think outside the KM box to create a program that brings value to your organization and hear how two organizations faced challenges, had success, and share lessons learned.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Lapachet</last_name>
          <first_name>Jaye A. H.</first_name>
          <job_title>Manager of Library Services</job_title>
          <works_for>Coblentz, Patch, Duffy &amp;amp; Bass LLP</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>MLS</last_name>
          <first_name>Camille Reynolds</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Knowledge Management, Nossaman LLP</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Bryan</last_name>
          <first_name>Eric</first_name>
          <job_title>Knowledge Sharing Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Boeing Company</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Gillis</last_name>
          <first_name>Angela</first_name>
          <job_title>Knowledge Sharing Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Boeing Company</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>McAllister</last_name>
          <first_name>Robert</first_name>
          <job_title>Knowledge Sharing Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Boeing Company</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Networking Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C204 &#x96; Integrating Content for Creative Products &amp;amp; Services</title>
      <description>Many digital publications and databases traditionally licensed by libraries are offering mobile versions of their products, sometimes free and sometimes for an additional price. How do we manage expectations of our clients and provide access to a growing number of mobile products? How do we add iPhone apps to the library catalogs? Hear how The World Bank library is addressing these questions to satisfy its clients who are highly mobile and demand the latest apps. Citation analysis&#x2014;once the domain of academic circles&#x2014;is gaining a foothold in private research organizations, both as an evaluative metric and&#xA0; corporate promotional tool. Hear how one library is developing a suite of features to bring citation analysis into regular use by its customers, how it is implementing valueadded features of citation alerting for patrons, RSS feeds of organization-affiliated journal article publishing, citation impact profiles of researchers, and more.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Maslyukova</last_name>
          <first_name>Elena</first_name>
          <job_title>Information Officer</job_title>
          <works_for>The World Bank</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Connell</last_name>
          <first_name>Christopher J.</first_name>
          <job_title>Information Integration Analyst</job_title>
          <works_for>Library, Institute for Defense Analyses</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C205 &#x96; Social Media Lessons From the Ad World &amp;amp; More!</title>
      <description>Social media is a noisy and crowded place filled with numerous companies blasting their message. How will you make sure your user community hears your voice? Based on successful strategies from the advertising world, the first presentation talks about how storytelling through social media has proven to engage users to contribute, share, and stay involved with the social media brand. It reflects a marketer perspective to showcase innovative social media initiatives that have gone viral and had received the attention of millions of people. What take-aways info pros can utilize from these campaigns to amplify a social media presence and create conversations in their communities are discussed. The second presentation describes building a social network to replace Yahoo! Groups from concept and initial UX research to design and implementation, highlighting likes/dislikes, assessment results, and opportunities for similar development by other libraries.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Rosales</last_name>
          <first_name>Melissa</first_name>
          <job_title>Information Specialist</job_title>
          <works_for>TBWA\Chiat\Day</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Carlos</last_name>
          <first_name>Andrew</first_name>
          <job_title>STEM &amp;amp; Web Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>California State University, East Bay</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Snell</last_name>
          <first_name>Jeremy</first_name>
          <job_title>Web &amp;amp; Electronic Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Mechanics' Institute</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Montgomery</last_name>
          <first_name>Matt</first_name>
          <job_title>Technical Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Mechanics' Institute</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Coffe Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D201 &#x96; Playing in the Community Sandbox</title>
      <description>This session shares Douglas County Libraries&#x2019; experience with several successful collaborations. Together with a major database vendor, it collaborated with the local school system to meet the electronic resource needs of the 55,000 students, increase their database use, and save taxpayers $100,000 in the process. At the same time, the library worked with chambers of commerce and local economic development councils to provide startup and marketing information to small-to mid-size companies. It has paired with the local election office to provide assistance with election questions. And an innovative program now allows library patrons to check out a pass to local art and wildlife museums. This session describes how its involvement in the community raises library awareness, fosters a sense of community, and adds value beyond the walls of the library. Get lots of tips and tricks to try in your environment.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Tibbetts</last_name>
          <first_name>Hutch</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Resources Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>IT &amp;amp; Web Services, Douglas County Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D202 &#x96; Collaborating: Students &amp;amp; Librarians</title>
      <description>From LibGuides to Facebook, Sakai to Skype, one university library has reinvented the way it reaches out to students &#x2014; based on what the students want. Following a series of focus groups with undergraduates and a massive assessment of library services, the library has become wired within the campus community. More than just an improvement to its online presence, the goal included getting what its users want within its walls. The first talk covers how staff learned to ask the right questions, gather feedback, get institutional buy-in and adapt a concept of perpetual beta. Kurt discusses how librarians at NR were inspired by Apple Stores&#x2019; display and customer service model and collaborated to create the @One eReader Bar where users can explore various handheld devices and learn what is possible, including making use of library e-resources via eReaders. The librarians acquired devices; researched, tested, and tracked how each worked and shared their findings with each other; designed an eReader Bar LibGuide; trained additional staff; and created informational materials.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Jacobs-Lustig</last_name>
          <first_name>Michelle</first_name>
          <job_title>Librarian for Instructional Design</job_title>
          <works_for>Outreach and Training, Pepperdine University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Kurt</last_name>
          <first_name>Lisa</first_name>
          <job_title>Emerging Technologies Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Nevada, Reno</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D203 &#x96; Engaging Communities With Collaboration</title>
      <description>Hear about the implementation of a local installation of WordPress to provide small public libraries throughout the state with free websites, since more than 100 public libraries in Nebraska had no noticeable web presence. Sauers shares lessons learned with the technology and work involved, the reactions of the participating libraries, challenges, and future plans. Mahajan discusses a collaborative effort to create Information Connections, a website for parents of children with developmental disabilities and chronic diseases, with funding from the National Library of Medicine. She highlights how the hospital developed needs assessment tools, designed a navigational architecture, and developed the information portal to resources and websites with a special focus on autism, cerebral palsy, ADHD, Down syndrome, and traumatic brain injury, among others. Having access to reliable, high-quality health information and local resources provides emotional support to families, especially during stressful times, and provides resources for healthcare providers, colleges and universities, schools, libraries, and hospitals at points of care or at home.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Sauers</last_name>
          <first_name>Michael P</first_name>
          <job_title>Technology Innovation Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Technology &amp;amp; Access Services, Nebraska Library Commission</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Mahajan</last_name>
          <first_name>Nalini</first_name>
          <job_title>Medical Library Director and Webmaster</job_title>
          <works_for>Marianjoy Rehabilitation Hospital</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Networking Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D204 &#x96; Partnerships &amp;amp; Relationships for Impact</title>
      <description>Today&#x2019;s academic landscape is&#xA0; constantly shaped by dramatically shrinking resources and an ever growing need to keep pace with the demands of users and changing technologies. Price and Harden discuss a strong partnership between public and electronic services departments that created many successful relationships throughout the campus, including both tangible and intangible returns to all parties, and allowed the library to showcase its sometimes overlooked but valuable services and resources. They illustrate how student internships harnessed a &#x201C;low-cost&#x201D; resource with virtually unlimited potential, a tremendous return on their investment &#x2014; time. As the students grow in knowledge, confidence, and abilities, staff interactions and conversations provide new and innovative ideas that could never have been implemented without them. From video production, to website development, to graphic design, our students do it all! Find out how the library empowers, nurtures, and challenges student interns while harnessing their unlimited potential to help show value and meet the growing demands of users. Sarnowski outlines successful &#x201C;Scan Day&#x201D; events held at libraries in the Midwest, where local historic photos, collectible souvenir postcards, and other artifacts were digitally captured during library-sponsored community events. He discusses equipment, training materials, and recommendations for staffing and procedures, as well as examples of the scans and the metadata that were produced, as well as a tour of the resulting websites. Generating local digital collections with standardized metadata while hosting a community event can be a great way to engage the public and add value to local and regional archives and library online catalogs and websites.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Price</last_name>
          <first_name>Anne</first_name>
          <job_title>Public Services Librarian/Associate Professor</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Mary Hardin-Baylor</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Harden</last_name>
          <first_name>Kathy</first_name>
          <job_title>Electronic Services Librarian/Associate Professor</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Mary Hardin-Baylor</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Sarnowski</last_name>
          <first_name>John</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>ResCarta Foundation</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D205 &#x96; Repositioning With Tablets, Social Media, &amp;amp; Outreach</title>
      <description>Speakers share how they repositioned their services with various devices and strategies.&#xA0; Donahue looks at the newest tablet designs, their operating systems and browsers, and explores the fresh possibilities they offer for discovery and access of library content. In addition to being one of the first libraries to develop a social media policy, Multnomah County Library was named one of the top library Facebook pages in 2010, and is one of the top five most fanned public libraries in the U.S. Speakers share their secrets of success, challenges, suggestions for developing strategies, campaigns and policy to make your online presence the best it can be! Cho discusses repositioning the academic library through community outreach, specifically the Chinese Canadian Stories: Uncommon Histories from a Common Past project, to expand the engagement between academic research and the communities which the university serves. Through the collaboration of community organizations across Canada and the the University of British Columbia Library, this one-of-a kind project gathers the ignored histories of one of the "founding peoples" of Canada and uses the latest in new media technologies to present a new understanding of our common history</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Donahue</last_name>
          <first_name>Tim</first_name>
          <job_title>Instruction Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Montana State University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Keller</last_name>
          <first_name>Arlene</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Services Coordinator</job_title>
          <works_for>Marketing + Online Engagement, Multnomah County Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Cho</last_name>
          <first_name>Allan</first_name>
          <job_title>Program Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of British Columbia Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Coffe Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>E201 &#x96; Mindful and Connected- Teaching Mindfulness at a 1:1 Laptop School</title>
      <description>As school librarians and educators, you teach your students tricks and tips for using online tools effectively for research. But today&#x2019;s students are digitally connected in all aspects of their lives, and there is reason to be concerned about the persuasive distraction of technology. As educators, you are in a unique position to encourage awareness of just how your students are using all that ubiquitous technology. In this session, find out from Shaw how a 1:1 laptop school&#x2014;with guidance from its librarian!&#x2014;has integrated mindfulness education into its culture.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Shaw</last_name>
          <first_name>Rachel</first_name>
          <job_title>Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>The Bay School</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>E202 &#x96; Helping Students Understand and Manage Their Digital Footprint</title>
      <description>Students are savvy about using the internet, but they often don&#x2019;t understand how their internet usage today impacts their lives tomorrow. In this session, learn from school librarian Nockowitz how to help your students create and maintain a positive digital footprint. She discusses how social networking, content creation, and social media are shaping students&#x2019; online personae and offers specific steps teachers and librarians can take to guide students in the right direction.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Nockowitz</last_name>
          <first_name>Stacy</first_name>
          <job_title>Middle School Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>The Columbus Academy</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>E203 &#x96; iPads, iPods, and E-Readers in the School Library</title>
      <description>Emerging technologies are constantly shifting the ways school libraries function. Whether making changes in the way content is viewed or allowing the curriculum to be taught in entirely new ways, school libraries must stay current. In this hour-long session, Renazile and Johnson, librarians at the School at Columbia University, talk about the practical ways they are using iPads and e-readers in their school library starting in kindergarten. Here are some of the discussion topics: How can iPads and iPods be tools for recommending books? What are some of the management issues of using iPads in the library? How can Twitter increase comprehension and conversation in book clubs? Next, technology director Ramig weighs in with more on iPads in her Seven Hills School program, where she finds them to be &#x201C;super-portable, instant-on, $500 devices that are perfect for school libraries.&#x201D;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Renazile</last_name>
          <first_name>Nadine</first_name>
          <job_title>Lead Librarian Grades 5-8</job_title>
          <works_for>The School at Columbia University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Johnson</last_name>
          <first_name>Tabitha</first_name>
          <job_title>Lead Librarian Grades K-4</job_title>
          <works_for>The School at Columbia University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Ramig</last_name>
          <first_name>Renee</first_name>
          <job_title>Director of Technology</job_title>
          <works_for>Seven Hills School</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Networking Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>E204 &#x96; The Library/Tech Connection: Making Collaboration Practical</title>
      <description>As libraries emerge into technologically based spaces, the connection between the technology department and the library/media center becomes vital. How do we collaborate and share best practices in both fields in order to make our students thoughtful and creative users of information? Thomas, lower school technology coordinator, and Ingham, lower school librarian, at Oregon Episcopal School, share stories and ideas about how they make their partnership work in the face of daily schedules, student and teacher demands, and the challenge of balancing interests and different personal/professional skill sets.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Ingham</last_name>
          <first_name>Lara</first_name>
          <job_title>Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Oregon Episcopal School</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Bodio-Thomas</last_name>
          <first_name>Debra</first_name>
          <job_title>Technology Coordinator</job_title>
          <works_for>Oregon Episcopal School</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>E205 &#x96; Down With Techno-Fear! Positive Steps to Counter Negative Times</title>
      <description>The new millennium has been filled with changes, many of which are downright scary. Consider the current threat level set by Homeland Security, the latest natural disaster news trumpeted by the media &#x2026; Meanwhile the economy lurches along. For educators at all levels, things can look bleak. Forget new equipment, enrichment experiences for students, travel to conferences. Many of us are just praying to hold on to our jobs. In this closing session of the Internet@Schools track, Professor and sage Bell speaks to this climate of unease, specifically offering ways to address the following &#x201C;techno-fears&#x201D;: 1. Fear of allowing our youngsters access to internet information by imposing draconian filters. 2. Fear of communication as well as information&#x2014;fear that causes many to recoil from any sort of online &#x201C;social networking.&#x201D; 3. Fear of letting our youngsters out of our virtual supervision for even a minute or two. 4. Fear of allowing students and kids have and use the devices that they all use so expertly. Mary Ann sends you off feeling fortified, if not fearless!</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Bell</last_name>
          <first_name>Mary Ann</first_name>
          <job_title>Professor of Library Science/</job_title>
          <works_for>Sam Houston State University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>The Great Web 2.0 Face-Off</title>
      <description>There are tools, tools, tools, but this event features learn, learn, learn while having fun! Our panel has ideas, but be sure to bring yours too! If we want to improve collaborative work, productivity, data representation, and research, what are the best Web 2.0 tools to use?&lt;strong&gt;The Game Plan!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;Three periods of play jam-packed with ideas, tips and tricks &#x2014; and even penalties and power plays! Team 1 (Blue Jerseys) takes on Team 2 (Red Jerseys) with captains and players while referees keep the pace going, and there is additional color commentary and expert analysis between periods. The game will be fast-paced, so be ready to tweet your cheers.Host: Anita Brooks Kirkland, Consultant, Information Technology Services, K-12 Libraries, Waterloo Region District School Board &lt;br&gt;Expert Analyst: Darlene Fichter, University of Saskatchewan&#xA0; [there will be another one if you want to leave room] &lt;br&gt;Color Commentator: Stephen Abram, Gale Cengage Learning &lt;br&gt;Red Team Captain: Amy Buckland, McGill University &lt;br&gt;Blue Team Captain: Blake Carver, LISHost.org &lt;br&gt;There will be players for both the teams which we are working on. &lt;br&gt;Technical Directors: Jane Dysart, JD Thomas &amp;amp; Kathy Hogan Bayer</description>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>OPENING KEYNOTE &#x97; Internet 2020: TrendWatch Smackdown</title>
      <description>This interactive, exciting, and free-wheeling discussion of all things tech looks at what&#x2019;s hot on the internet landscape and what&#x2019;s ahead. Werle talks about next-gen broadband applications and how Internet2, the U.S. fabric of not-for-profit research and education networks, is helping remove bandwidth constraints so public libraries and other community anchor organizations can make new technologies, learning experiences and community collaborations, rich educational content, and workforce development opportunities a reality for people within their community no matter where they&#x2019;re located. Social computing expert Lawley shares her insights about the internet in 2020, and internet industry watcher, Abram highlights shifts and sea changes that he sees coming our way. Definitely a session to jump-start your future focus.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Tennant</last_name>
          <first_name>Roy</first_name>
          <job_title>Senior Program Officer</job_title>
          <works_for>Research, OCLC Online Computer Library Center, Inc.</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Werle</last_name>
          <first_name>James</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Internet2 K20 Initiative, Internet2</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Lawley</last_name>
          <first_name>Elizabeth Lane</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>RIT Lab for Social Computing, Rochester Institute of Technology</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Abram</last_name>
          <first_name>Stephen</first_name>
          <job_title>Principal</job_title>
          <works_for>Lighthouse Consulting Inc.</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A301 &amp;amp; A302 &#x96; Talk About: Publishers, Distributors &amp;amp; the Future of Ebooks</title>
      <description>Although we are calling them ebooks, electronic versions of works are quite unlike their print-based counterparts. &#xA0;To force an electronic resource to behave like a print resource is an exercise in frustration; does each have a role to play now and in the future? The way ebooks are sold by publishers and distributors, and the terms of use of institutions serving the public are getting lots of attention. &#xA0;Join the collaborative conversation around these issues and be a part of this interactive discussion to understand various points of view of publishers, distributors, libraries, and new organizations looking to find creative solutions! &#xA0;</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Griffin</last_name>
          <first_name>Alison</first_name>
          <job_title>Account Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Ingram&#x92;s Coutts Library Service</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Porter</last_name>
          <first_name>Michael</first_name>
          <job_title>President</job_title>
          <works_for>Library Renewal libraryman.com</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Miller</last_name>
          <first_name>Robert</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Books, Internet Archive</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Houghton</last_name>
          <first_name>Sarah</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>San Rafael Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Yelton</last_name>
          <first_name>Andromeda</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Projects and Library Outreach</job_title>
          <works_for>Gluejar</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Gurewitz</last_name>
          <first_name>Brian</first_name>
          <job_title>Director of Content Sales</job_title>
          <works_for>OverDrive</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A303 &#x96; Practical Considerations for Public &amp;amp; Academic Libraries</title>
      <description>Ebooks are used differently depending upon the users the library serves. Join our panel of experts from college and public library systems to hear them discuss how they decide if and when to include ebooks in their collections and within their curriculum, as well as current issues and challenges that they face and expect to face into the future.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Mairn</last_name>
          <first_name>Chad</first_name>
          <job_title>Information Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>St. Petersburg College</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Ciccone</last_name>
          <first_name>Michael</first_name>
          <job_title>Director of Collections</job_title>
          <works_for>Hamilton Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Polanka</last_name>
          <first_name>Sue</first_name>
          <job_title>Head of Reference and Instruction</job_title>
          <works_for>Wright State University Libraries No Shelf Required</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>A304 &#x96; Ebook Issues &amp;amp; Challenges: Debrief</title>
      <description>This interactive session with a panel of rapporteurs, wraps up Internet Librarian&#x2019;s 2-day focus on libraries and ebooks: by reviewing the highlights, pulling future actions to the forefront, noting areas for future research for discussion, and more.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Kaser</last_name>
          <first_name>Dick</first_name>
          <job_title>Vice President of Content</job_title>
          <works_for>Information Today</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Roberts</last_name>
          <first_name>Ken</first_name>
          <job_title>Consultant</job_title>
          <works_for>Ken Roberts Library Consulting  &amp;amp; former Chief Librarian, Hamilton Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Murphy</last_name>
          <first_name>Joe</first_name>
          <job_title>Library Directions &amp;amp; Tech Trends Analyst. Director Library Futures.</job_title>
          <works_for>Library Future Innovative Interfaces, Yale Uni</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Walker</last_name>
          <first_name>Aspen</first_name>
          <job_title>Library Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Castle Pines &amp;amp; Lone Tree Libraries, Douglas County Libraries SaveLibraries.org, Colorado Association of Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B301 &#x96; Tech Change</title>
      <description>Affelt speculates what tech changes we will see from 2011 to 2021 and explores current thinking on emerging technologies for finding, accessing, and providing information. Both the Horizon Report 2011 and ACRL&#x2019;s report, &#x201C;Futures Thinking for Academic Librarians: Higher Education in 2025,&#x201D; list gesture-based computing as a trend to watch and adopt in a few years. Menon and Koury discuss what has been done in a number of U.S. and European libraries, what is coming, and what is on our wish list when it comes to gesture-based computing.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Affelt</last_name>
          <first_name>Amy</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Database Research, Compass Lexecon</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Menon</last_name>
          <first_name>Amalia</first_name>
          <job_title>University Head Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Olivet University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Koury</last_name>
          <first_name>Regina</first_name>
          <job_title>Head of Collection Management</job_title>
          <works_for>Idaho State University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B302 &#x96; FutureReady365: Highlights, Insights, &amp;amp; Advice</title>
      <description>SLA&#x2019;s 2011 initiative encourages members to become Future Ready by adopting an attitude of being more adaptable, flexible, and confident in utilizing their skills in the new knowledge economy. An active community blog FutureReady365 is focused on sharing knowledge, ideas, and insights on how we are ready for the future. It includes different perspectives &#x2014; members, vendors, partners, thought leaders and clients &#x2014; so that we get a multidimensional view of what Future Ready looks like to inspire one another. Romaine shares the hot-button issues, weighted advice, and insights (appropriate for any information professional) gleaned from the experience of executing a daily, collaborative, distributed social networking project.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Romaine</last_name>
          <first_name>Cindy</first_name>
          <job_title>Principal</job_title>
          <works_for>Romainiacs Intelligence Research &amp;amp; President, SLA</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Cole</last_name>
          <first_name>Meryl</first_name>
          <job_title>Principal</job_title>
          <works_for>Masterminds Strategic Research</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B303 &#x96; Imagining a Future for the Library Catalog</title>
      <description>The current model of the library catalog as a self-contained destination where patrons must go to search for content dooms the catalog to a future of irrelevance and obscurity. We (librarians &amp;amp; ILS vendors) must re-imagine the catalog not as a destination but as a source for the highest-quality data, and then freely share that data with search engines and other applications using a wide range of current and future technologies and techniques. What&#x2019;s beyond the next-gen catalog? What&#x2019;s our future?</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Nelson</last_name>
          <first_name>Walter T</first_name>
          <job_title>Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Library Systems, RAND Corporation</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Breeding</last_name>
          <first_name>Marshall</first_name>
          <job_title>Independent Consultant and Founder of Library Technology Guides</job_title>
          <works_for>Founder of Library Technology Guides</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Pace</last_name>
          <first_name>Andrew K</first_name>
          <job_title>Executive Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Networked Library Services, OCLC Online Computer Library Center, Inc.</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>B304 &#x96; Storytelling Tools on Multitouch Solutions</title>
      <description>Storytelling tools as designed by DOKLAB, an innovation lab and home of our speakers, also known as The Shanachies, are appealing, mostly digital, products and services that connect users, the providers of all sorts of stories (content). Storytelling tools make it easy and fun to find information, as well as collect and share stories both within and outside the library walls. These tools come in many shapes and forms, so come hear about these exciting new multitouch solutions.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Boekesteijn</last_name>
          <first_name>Erik</first_name>
          <job_title>founder and director Doklab</job_title>
          <works_for>Doklab ShanachieTour</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Geer</last_name>
          <first_name>Jaap Van de</first_name>
          <job_title>Delft Public Library</job_title>
          <works_for>D</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C301 &#x96; Inno'play'ion in Libraries</title>
      <description>Are you seeking inspiration for some new models and practices to ignite your library services and community? Is your organization ready to move beyond implementing best practices to develop your own fresh practices but feel stuck in old paradigm thinking? You are not alone. Join Blowers in exploring the intersection of &#x201C;innovation&#x201D; and &#x201C;play&#x201D; and discover some new ways to apply technology and think about libraries, services, and knowledge sharing. Create an inno&#x201D;play&#x201D;ion spark to jump-start your thinking.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Blowers</last_name>
          <first_name>Helene</first_name>
          <job_title>Community Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>OCLC</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C302 &#x96; Strengthening Community, Enhancing Library Services</title>
      <description>EPL embarked on an ambitious process to implement a community-led service framework reflecting its commitment to meeting customer needs and reducing barriers. It recruited 13 community librarians and transitioned more traditional librarian roles to a community-led focus. Hear stories of how EPL has made a difference within the community. The second presentation illustrates how rearranging a public library to be more like a bookstore grabbed community attention.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Martinez</last_name>
          <first_name>Pilar</first_name>
          <job_title>Executive Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Public Services, Edmonton Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Hosseini-Ara</last_name>
          <first_name>Moe</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Culture, City of Markham Markham Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Garvin</last_name>
          <first_name>Linda</first_name>
          <job_title>Chair</job_title>
          <works_for>Community Led Service Philosophy Team, Edmonton Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C303 &#x96; Building a Think Tank @ Your Library</title>
      <description>Innovation and new services can come from all levels of your organization. First, learn how a public and academic library create structures of participation ranging from brown bag talks to dedicated working groups to drive new services and create beta projects. Clark talks about the creation of an emerging technologies think tank at Montana State University Library. Caserotti shares her experience running Tech Bites, staff-led technology training lunches at Darien Library. Come see how you might create these structures of participation. The CPL team shares how their Future Action Team (FAT) was established to support the development of organizational change champions and to provide opportunities for emerging leaders to influence the library&#x2019;s strategic direction.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Clark</last_name>
          <first_name>Jason A.</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Initiatives Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>Head of Digital Access and Web Services, Montana State University Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Caserotti</last_name>
          <first_name>Gretchen</first_name>
          <job_title>Assistant Director for Public Services</job_title>
          <works_for>Darien Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>MacKenzie</last_name>
          <first_name>Nancy</first_name>
          <job_title>Customer Service Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Calgary Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Hardy</last_name>
          <first_name>Lisa</first_name>
          <job_title>Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>West Sector, Calgary Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>C304 &#x96; Web Services: Libraries in the Cloud</title>
      <description>By moving routine tasks (like acquisitions and circulation) to the web, libraries are able to share infrastructure costs and resources, as well as collaborate in new ways and without the restrictions of local hardware and software. Hear how libraries are using web services and the impact it is having on their libraries.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Pace</last_name>
          <first_name>Andrew K</first_name>
          <job_title>Executive Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Networked Library Services, OCLC Online Computer Library Center, Inc.</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Haight</last_name>
          <first_name>Larry</first_name>
          <job_title>Director of Libraries</job_title>
          <works_for>Simpson University</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Hartman</last_name>
          <first_name>Robin</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Library Services, Hope International University</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D301 &#x96; Building Support for Change &amp;amp; Customer Relationships</title>
      <description>Hear how VPL is increasing technology training, providing more computers, and leading support of electronic resources and ebooks during a difficult budget climate. Their secret &#x2014; a highly collaborative process, public consultation, evaluation, and experimentation to successfully transform a low-use, print-based environment into a technology-focused learning space. Find out the surprises from patrons, what worked and what didn&#x2019;t, and learn what you can apply to public technology training and support. Then hear how Texas A&amp;amp;M University Libraries replaced its homegrown &#x201C;help desk&#x201D; problem tracking system of more than 10 years with SugarCRM, an enterprise class open source customer relationship management platform. As service organizations, libraries are especially sensitive to customer feedback, relationships, and keeping their fingers on the pulse of customer needs. Learn what factors drove the decisions to go with a CRM for the libraries&#x2019; internal customers, how buy-in was achieved, experiences so far, and plans for the future.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Castell</last_name>
          <first_name>Christina de</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Resources &amp;amp; Technology, Vancouver Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Armstrong</last_name>
          <first_name>Tommy</first_name>
          <job_title>Senior Systems Analyst and Information Architect</job_title>
          <works_for>Texas A&amp;amp;M University Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Hahn</last_name>
          <first_name>Doug</first_name>
          <job_title>Senior IT Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Texas A&amp;amp;M University Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D302 &#x96; Social Media Strategy &amp;amp; Goals</title>
      <description>Organizations are great at starting new online projects ... and then letting them quickly die. Do you know how to plan, sustain, and set goals for an online project? This session describes the planning processes used by several different libraries &#x2014; how they plan, create strategy, get buy-in, and sustain a social media project.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>King</last_name>
          <first_name>David Lee</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital Services Director</job_title>
          <works_for>Topeka &amp;amp; Shawnee County Public Library and Publisher, davidleeking.com</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D303 &#x96; Getting Things Done - Tips &amp;amp; Tricks</title>
      <description>This panel shares tips and techniques for accomplishing the many task and challenges that libraries face. Westbrook describes how a small staff with ambitious plans tripled their workforce and implemented robust project tracking workflows &#x2014; all without spending a cent by creating an online management system (OMS) that harnesses freely available Web 2.0 tools to collaboratively manage a rotating pool of library school interns. Houghton-Jan, an expert in project persuasion, shares useful tricks for getting technology projects past intractable committees, grumpy bosses, anti-technology supervisors, and change-resistant staff, as well as Jedi mind tricks, psychological gambits, and convincing arguments that you too can use to get stuff done. Harris addresses best practices for using the internet to develop accountability factors for your library &#x2014; goal setting, project management, and creating an organizational culture of transparency.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Westbrook</last_name>
          <first_name>R. Niccole</first_name>
          <job_title>Coordinator of Digital Operations</job_title>
          <works_for>Digital Services Department, University of Houston Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Houghton</last_name>
          <first_name>Sarah</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>San Rafael Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Harris</last_name>
          <first_name>Colleen S.</first_name>
          <job_title>Head of Access Services</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Tennessee &#x96; Chattanooga</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>D304 &#x96; Using Data for Library Success</title>
      <description>With today&#x2019;s limited resources and increasing demand for services, it&#x2019;s more important than ever that libraries think like a business. One of the best ways to do this is using the information already available, in the form of data, whether it&#x2019;s stored on a computer system, entered into a spreadsheet, or handwritten. Business intelligence (BI) provides the key decision makers in the organization with the data they need, when they need it, and in a format that enables quick decisions. BI utilizes technology and processes to gather, analyze, and present data that can be used to support operational and strategic decision making. BI can tell you how the organization is performing today and provide insight into how it could look in the future. Learn how the Columbus Metropolitan Library (CML) is utilizing BI to control costs, improve service to customers, and better utilize resources. The presenters will discuss the concepts and technologies of BI and show examples of how BI has streamlined its decision making process.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Syferd</last_name>
          <first_name>Greg</first_name>
          <job_title>Systems Administration Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Information Technology, Columbus Metropolitan Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Turner</last_name>
          <first_name>Wendy</first_name>
          <job_title>IT Business Analyst</job_title>
          <works_for>Columbus Metropolitan Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>E301 &#x96; Digital Content Tools: Thesaurus &amp;amp; Folksonomies</title>
      <description>Are you starting a digital library project? Are you interested in taxonomies and folksonomies? Whether you&#x2019;re digitizing historical photographs, creating subject guides, or organizing your library&#x2019;s blog, building a thesaurus is an investment that will help your users find what they need. The first presentation discusses how a well-designed thesaurus can drive browsing and searching, display cross-references, help populate metadata, and highlight popular content. It provides tips for using the words your users prefer by bridging the taxonomy-folksonomy gap. The second presentation showcases bookmarking alternatives, such as Pinboard.in, ZooTools, Folkd, Knowledge Plaza, Diigo, etc., and talks about the issues of social tag implementation, taxonomy-based tags, and how to guide users on how to generate better tags. These findings are based on social tag content management experience from an online social network. Join our knowledgeable speakers to learn some tips and tricks for creating a controlled vocabulary that will grow with your project.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Madler</last_name>
          <first_name>Aubrey</first_name>
          <job_title>Information Specialist</job_title>
          <works_for>Rural Assistance Center (RAC)</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Rosales</last_name>
          <first_name>Melissa</first_name>
          <job_title>Information Specialist</job_title>
          <works_for>TBWA\Chiat\Day</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Carlos</last_name>
          <first_name>Andrew</first_name>
          <job_title>STEM &amp;amp; Web Services Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>California State University, East Bay</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>E302 &#x96; Making a Case for CMS!</title>
      <description>Making a convincing case to change from non- or lightly-managed web sites to a content management system (CMS) can seem daunting. However, you can build a strong case that will help convince administration of the benefits of CMSs. In this talk, two librarians who manage large public and internal websites at the University of Michigan and the University of Colorado Denver give you all of the ammo you need! Gain insight on why having a CMS is better than not having one and why an open source CMS tool (such as Drupal and MediaWiki) are viable, functional, and efficient solutions. Audience participation in the form of group therapy will be encouraged!</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Varnum</last_name>
          <first_name>Ken</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Systems Manager</job_title>
          <works_for>Library Information Technology, University of Michigan Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>McHale</last_name>
          <first_name>Nina</first_name>
          <job_title>Web Developer</job_title>
          <works_for>Digital Services, Arapahoe Library District</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>Lunch Break - A Chance to Visit the Exhibits</title>
      <description/>
      <speakers/>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>E303 &#x96; Data Management, Preservation, Curation, &amp;amp; Repositories</title>
      <description>The management, preservation, and curation of research data is one of the hottest topics in librarianship today. Peters and Riley discuss their assessment of current data curation practices and grant-related data management plan preparedness on the part of their university researchers, identify the types and volume of data produced by research grants as well as specific technologies, metadata schemas, and archiving practices that are in use on campus. They hope this is a first step towards creating a centralized solution for managing and preserving research data in conjunction with other campus units. &#xA0;Perry discusses digital preservation strategies and curation flows. &#xA0;Gunn contributes to the data curation discussion and talks&#xA0;about embedding institutional data into the researcher's workflow,&#xA0;and the effect of design and usability work on tool usage.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Peters</last_name>
          <first_name>Christie</first_name>
          <job_title>Science &amp;amp; Engineering Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Houston</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Dasler</last_name>
          <first_name>Robin</first_name>
          <job_title>Science and Mathematics Librarian</job_title>
          <works_for>University of Houston</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Dryden</last_name>
          <first_name>Anita R.</first_name>
          <job_title>Digital &amp;amp; Web Projects Fellow</job_title>
          <works_for>Unviersity of Houston Libraries</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Perry</last_name>
          <first_name>Susan Chesley</first_name>
          <job_title>Head of Digital Initiatives</job_title>
          <works_for>University Library, University of California, Santa Cruz</works_for>
        </speaker>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>PhD</last_name>
          <first_name>William Gunn</first_name>
          <job_title>Head</job_title>
          <works_for>Academic Research, Mendeley Ltd</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>E304 &#x96; Digital Content Frustration: Copyright, Licensing, &amp;amp; DRM</title>
      <description>Digital content licensing is confusing at best for consumers and for library purchasers. Authors, musicians, and filmmakers create content, and people want to consume that content. In the middle, though, are publishers and content aggregators which add rules of use to digital content that differ from the rules of use for the same content in a physical format. How can libraries successfully navigate this web of difficulty and advocate for our users? This session covers the basics of copyright law as it applies to digital content as well as the impact of licensing/terms and conditions from different content providers and publishers. Find out how all of this legalese affects the implementation of digital rights management technology on both consumer and library licensed digital content. You will also learn a bit about piracy and resources for breaking digital rights management for legal backup copies. Come away with a toolkit to explain complicated rules to coworkers and users.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Houghton</last_name>
          <first_name>Sarah</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>San Rafael Public Library</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
    <session>
      <title>CLOSING KEYNOTE &#x97; Gamification: The Good, the Bad, and the Ugly</title>
      <description>&#x201C;Gamification&#x201D; is a hot new term in business and tech circles these days, and you can find as many people vilifying as praising it. What does it really mean to &#x201C;gamify&#x201D; something? What value can this increasing focus on game mechanics in nontraditional contexts bring, and what risks accompany it? Lawley talks about this phenomenon, sharing experiences from past and current game design efforts she&#x2019;s been involved in.</description>
      <speakers>
        <speaker>
          <last_name>Lawley</last_name>
          <first_name>Elizabeth Lane</first_name>
          <job_title>Director</job_title>
          <works_for>RIT Lab for Social Computing, Rochester Institute of Technology</works_for>
        </speaker>
      </speakers>
    </session>
  </sessions>
</conference>
